Uh good morning. We are
uh live.
Um so
uh we read your comments yesterday
and um there are three concerns. The
first the major concern is a sound
quality. So uh Carol and her team are
fixing that. Um second is that there are
parts of the video missing because of
network issues. And so what Carol and
her team are going to do is upload uh um
the complete version uh later today or
whenever it's ready. Um and the third
issue is
um the quality of the resolution, the
resolution quality. Unfortunately,
because it's a live stream, we have to
lower the resolution in order to make it
more smooth, but we will upload uh a
higher quality version later on. Okay.
So, thanks so much to Carol and her team
for making this possible. And um um so
we are going to continue the line calm
meeting today. But before I begin,
are there any questions
or concerns from yesterday? Uh yes.
So uh yesterday we got to uh count to
four and five
>> five and my point is we were like over
four and in four I had this uh really
big question. So in K four uh they show
themselves to here not because this is
their sphere but as a sign for you that
in the inferion their place is lowest.
So what I take this section to mean is
that even though there's no difference
in accommodations, so like there's a
five-star hotel, there's a four-star
hotel and everyone goes to the five-star
hotel. However, there is a difference in
prestige as in their place is lowest. So
my question is uh if there is no
different difference in accommodations,
then why does God divide them into casts
of prestige?
>> Okay, great question. Okay. So um first
of all we are beyond time and space. So
everything is together. It's complete
unity. Unison. Okay. Does that make
sense? That's point one. Point two is
that everyone is with God in the
imperium.
That is what it is in reality. But to
make it comprehensible to Dante and to
us
um Beatrice has constructed the heavens
visually
in a hierarchy. Okay.
And then what is this hierarchy? This
hierarchy
is the amount of God that you receive in
your soul. Okay? So you are all in
heaven. You're all with God. But there
are certain souls that are able to
receive the light of God greater than
other souls.
And that is what the hierarchy is like.
The closer you are to God, the more you
are able to receive his light. The more
you are in communion with God.
And what differentiates
your ability to absorb God is your
understanding of your relationship with
God.
Okay. So Ricarda
is in the lowest sphere because she
thinks that she is unworthy of God. She
is unequal to God. Therefore she must
obey God.
But that's not what God wants. God is
all forgiving, all generous. He wants to
come into you and become you. So you
must welcome him. Ricardo is like, I'm
not worthy God. I am just a
mortal. Okay? And so what's happened is
she's placed herself further from God
because she thinks she's not worthy
enough to be closer to God. Okay? Does
that make sense?
Okay. So that's what it is in reality.
Um, but for us to better understand
this, uh, they've constructed a
hierarchy of spears and each spear has
its own distinct characteristics as
we'll see as we go along. Right. Any
more questions or Yes.
>> Um, okay. Okay, so I was just rereading
um Kanto one to four and there was a
couple of lines in Kanto 2 that caught
my attention because at least I found
them to be very interesting. So I'm
going to read it out to you guys. Um so
from line 23 to 25 it should be but in a
span perhaps no longer than an arrow
takes to strike to fly to leave. So
ideally I think the right order is first
for the arrow to leave the bow to fly
and then to strike. So why does Dante
kind of like intentionally reverse this
order in during this part of the text?
>> Okay. Um so first of all we are
beyond time and space meaning that what
what's happening here
in maybe our universe is just one second
or less than that. Okay so everything's
happening at once. Um and
um
so he's trying to show you the speed at
which things are happening. Okay.
Okay. Can you explain that? Um, I
actually need I don't have access to a
line. Let me
>> It's an KTO 2.
>> Yes.
>> From line 23 to uh 25.
>> Okay. Line 23 to 25.
>> Line 23 to 25.
>> Okay. Can you read it again?
>> Um, but in a span perhaps no longer than
an arrow takes to strike, to fly, to
leave the boat.
>> Um, I reached a place where I could see
that something wonderful drew me.
So, I'm just like interested why Dante
is reversing the order that typically an
arrow shoots out from a bow because it
should be first it leaves the bow, then
it flies, then finally it strikes.
Um okay so this is poetry and there are
different
uh
conceptions
okay but I think what he what he's doing
is he's collapsing time
does that make sense to you because as
you say the cover sequence events is you
first leave the bowl then You fly, then
you hit your target. Right? But then
he's saying, I first hit my target, then
I fly, then I leave. So I take this to
mean the collapse of time. Does that
make sense to you?
Yes. We are we are in a place where time
and space has collapsed altogether.
>> Yeah. So there's no time then there's no
space.
Right. So, so there there are the most
basic interpretation is that this is
happening so fast that it's beyond
perception. Do you understand? Because
because you because what we're seeing
it's human perception, right? It's the
human logic and and what what he's
saying is that this happening so fast
it's even beyond my perception.
But another way to interpret this is
it's h it's beyond your it's beyond your
perception because it's collapsing time
and space.
Okay. Does it make sense guys?
>> Can I offer like a thought?
>> Absolutely.
>> Um yesterday you put on your board where
there's a will there's a way.
>> And so in a way this reverse order kind
of um
enunciates the importance of the aim and
the goal first and then goes backwards.
And um yes, chronologically it's
different, but it's the you know, this
is inspired by commentary here too. It's
um kind of how things actually happen
because where there's a will, there's a
way. And you start with the goal first,
the end first.
>> Yes.
>> And then everything else proceeds.
>> Okay.
That's that's beautiful. Thank you. Yes.
Yes. Okay. So again, there are multiple
explanations, right? Good. Okay. Yes.
So, I hope to to add to that because um
as I was as I was biking home last
night, I was listening to um a book on
Einstein and the narrator connected it
to Dante just coincidentally. And
Einstein's working with space and time
and he had this kind of quip that said
time is what prevents everything from
happening at once. And then they said
much like Dante's Paradise where
everything can and does happen at once.
He didn't pull that line up
specifically, but I think that's the
answer that Einstein came up with.
>> Yes. Um, you know, I want to add to this
point and point out that the greatest
scientists,
um, they were first and foremost poets.
They were the ones who
were willing to imagine a new reality.
People like Newton and Einstein.
>> [clears throat]
>> So this is something that we've
forgotten where before science was
driven by the imagination, by intuition,
by poetry, by the occult, by by a desire
to be closer to God. And now we've
broken science into these logical
processes that are compartmentalized.
That's why honestly for the past 70
years, we've accomplished nothing. Okay?
We've had no breakthroughs for these
past 70 years. Okay? So thank you for
that. Any more questions before we we we
we begin? Yes.
This is more of a conceptual question.
So yesterday you emphasized to us
repeatedly the importance of imagination
and intuition. Now uh according to my
limited understanding, one of the
criticisms of the middle ages is that it
relied too much on mysticism and
unreason. So if Dante is like almost a
representative or a pioneer of the
Renaissance which is characterized in
opposition to the middle ages which must
therefore be comprised of reason and the
light of reason and rationality. Why is
Dante's work why does Dante's work
emphasize intuition and imagination in
such a way?
>> Okay. Um so we'll talk about this today.
Um but Dante is very much a
revolutionary. He's trying to respond to
limitations of his uh time and period.
And his major concern
is that the Catholic Church is involved
in geopolitics,
meaning that the Catholic Church is
trying to be the empire. And he doesn't
like that because it obviously creates a
lot of problems. It creates a lot of
wars.
Um, so
Donniey's primary concern is that as an
empire, the Catholic Church is not
focused enough on spirituality, not
focused enough on mysticism, on the
occult. It's more focused on temporal
power, on getting people to obey them.
And that's what limited the imagination
of medieval Europe. Okay. So we'll
discuss this more this morning but um
but does that answer your question for
now? Okay. Because our conception of the
Middle Ages is almost an anacronistic.
Okay. We're we're looking at from our
lens. Okay. But in my comedy we're
seeing it from Bond's lens. All right.
Uh question.
>> Yeah. Um, so, oh, this is really loud.
So, one like overall question maybe for
the book as well is um just I I still
don't really understand how he came up
with all of this like like did he did it
came to him like in a dream? Was it like
multiple dreams and then he then he
wrote them down or
>> Yeah.
>> Like did he just imagine it on his desk
like sitting on his desk or like walking
in a park or something? Like I like how
was it? So, and then so in-depth as well
like I I don't understand that.
>> Okay. So, there are two major themes
today. The first major theme is Dante's
revolution against Catholic Church.
Okay. What are what are his concerns
about the Catholic Church and what is he
trying to change about the Catholic
church? Okay, that's the first major
concern. Second major concern is how did
he write this? Because this is a time
about computers. This is a time where
pen and paper are not that accessible.
Okay. And he published it
um he published first the inferno in the
purgatory and then paradise. But you
read the divine comedy it is pretty
coherent. Okay. It's almost like he
first wrote everything down, then he uh
shaped
um the uh all three parts to be coherent
together to flow seamlessly. But we know
for a fact that's how it happened. So
the major question is how are you able
to even before you write anything down,
how are you able to structure in a way
that is mathematically perfect? Right?
So something that that we will not
probably discuss but something that we
should discuss more is the mathematics
the numerology of the divine comedy
where there are three sections the first
section is 34 contos second section is
section is 33 that's 100 also the number
33 has a lot of occult meaning because
33 is the age when Jesus died. Okay. Um
33 has a lot of occult um significance.
So this is like really weird. How was
able to even before I wrote anything
down mathematically conceive the
entirety
of the divine comedy?
And this is something that we will
address throughout these two weeks
because
it's really a question of what really is
our connection to the divine. Okay. So
something that I will argue to you today
is that
Dante could have only written this if
God exists. Okay? If God doesn't exist
and randomness randomness is what rules
the universe, there's no way he could
have written this. It makes absolutely
no sense. Only if he is able to channel
God, the monad, the source, whatever you
call it, is he able to write this down.
Okay?
And
um when we really try to understand
divine comedy, you will see that within
it is divinity itself. Okay. Okay. So,
so, so this is a question that is the
fundamental question we're trying to
address these next two weeks. Okay. But
thank you for that. Any more questions
before we begin?
Okay. Good. Okay. So yesterday we left
off with uh Picarda and the the the
Picarda presents an extremely complex
moral dilemma.
She did nothing wrong, right? She loved
God. She married God by become a nun.
Then her brother who is a duke or prince
I forget actually he needs her in order
to create a military alliance. So he
steals her from the convent and marries
her all and again she did nothing wrong
but she ends up in the low sphere of
paradise. Okay, so she's in heaven, but
it's a furthest from God.
And Donnie is like, "This makes no
sense. She right. She did everything the
Catholic Church told her to do. She
follow her heart and she ends up the
furthest from God." And what we said is
it's because she did not actually
practice her will. She did not show her
true faith in God, right? And there are
many things she she she could have done.
She could have ran away. She could have
threatened to kill herself. She could um
and so there are many things she could
have done. Okay? What I'm going to do
now is go deeper into this uh story
and show you how complex it is.
All right? And then we I want us to use
our imagination or intuition to figure
out what the proper choice would have
been. All right. So So let me explain
the um situation. Okay. All right. So So
let me set up for you. Okay. We know
that Picarda
has made a vow
to God. I'm going to marry you God. Um
and what Beatrice tells us is that
making of how is a very serious thing.
Making a promise is a very serious thing
because the greatest gift God has given
you is your free will. And when you
choose to surrender your free will as a
gift to God,
there's really nothing you can do to
compensate for breaking this vow. Okay?
So Ricarda, the issue is that she has a
vow to God.
All right.
Now, her brother,
and again, I don't know if this is
historically true, but I'm going to
create a situ a scenario for you guys,
okay? Her brother has a friend
and the two are trying to conquer Italy
together and they're in a battle. Okay?
And before this battle, the brother says
to the friend, you know, the Picard's
brother, if we win this battle, I swear
to God that I will give you my sister
as a bride. Okay, so it's another
battle, right? And they win the battle.
So that's that's that's a situation,
right? Her Carter has run off to a nery.
Her brother is like, "Oh, okay. I swore
to God that I would give my sister as a
bride. Therefore, I'm obliging my God to
do whatever I can to get her back. Okay?
Right? Because I I made a vow to God. Um
so now let us
think deeply, okay? and say let's say
for whatever reason both Picarda and her
brother have true faith in God meaning
they will do whatever they can to ensure
they do not break their vow to God right
so here we have Picarda saying you know
what I am on the roof and if you come
and get me from the nunny I will go jump
off the roof and kill myself I don't
care what the Catholic Church says says,
"Yes, I know it is the greatest in the
world to commit suicide. I understand
that. But my vow to God is greater than
the Catholic Church." Okay. And then the
brother's like, "Well, Picarda, I also
mean a vow to God
be and God has given me victory in
battle and therefore I cannot betray
God. God has already given me the gift
of victory in battle. So I must give you
to um uh my friend. Okay. So now what
we're going to do is we're going to use
your imagination and intuition to figure
out how first of all how this will play
out but also what is the proper or right
uh choice. Okay. So here is like you
know what if you come and get me I'm
going to kill myself. What's the brother
going to do?
Yeah. Um,
>> personally I think uh assuming that the
brother has true belief in God, I think
this hypothetical is a little bit weird
because as you mentioned before uh our
free will is our most precious gift from
God and only the only person you can
promise you can surrender your free will
to is the person who gave it to you as
in God. However, the brother here is
playing God. The brother here is
presuming on behalf of another to take
away her free will. I know that in the
Catholic church uh a wife swears
obedience to her husband upon marriage.
But this is the Catholic Church. This is
not Dante's God. So how dare this
brother who has true belief in God
presume to strip her his sister of her
free will?
>> Um
okay.
I I understand. But like Let's just play
this game, okay? Let's just first use
our imagination and play out this story,
okay? Let's let's imagine we're writing
a movie, right? And this make a great
movie, by the way. So, Ricardo is like,
I'm going to kill myself. What would the
brother do?
Well, I think definitely his her brother
going to save him because because the
brother have a commitment with his
friends. He need to win the battle. So I
believe in order to win the win the war
the brother will not allow her sister to
die. That is why his her brother going
to save Picarda if she want to suicide.
>> No no no no she's already dead like
>> oh she's already died.
>> No I'm saying like you come into the
comment I'm going to jump myself I'm
going to throw myself off the roof. I'm
going to kill myself. How how can he she
possibly he possibly save her? Okay. All
right. So here what he's going to do now
is say you know what Ricarda I'm going
to kidnap our mother. I'm going to kill
her unless you come out the covenant and
marry my friend, right?
>> That's something he would do.
>> Yeah.
>> Why couldn't he just marry his own
daughter or like another sister?
>> Because he made a vow, right? He said
before this battle, if we He saying this
to his friend, I swear to God, if we win
this battle, I will give you my sister
Ricarda as your bride. Okay. So he's
already made this vow.
All right. So
we are now now the situation is
the Duke presents their mother. Okay.
And says, "Hey, Picarda, you come down
now. I'm going to cut off her head."
Right.
>> He he go gets another brother. No. No.
Um, Picarda go gets their father and
then says, "If you kill our mother, I
will kill our father."
>> Okay guys, this is not how it works.
Okay,
so now it seems like Ricardo has no
choice, right?
Because I mean to kill yourself is one
thing, but to end up killing yourself
and your mother is something you cannot
possibly do. So what she does now is
surrender, right?
>> But if she believes in the will of God
and if she has will, she if she has
faith that God is standing on her side,
she'll have faith that her mother won't
die. So she'll still be standing on top.
>> Okay, let's just say she has complete
faith in God. The correct choice would
be to surrender. Why?
Okay. Because it's not just her, it's
her it's her mother. So if it's just
her, it's her choice to make. But if
it's her mother, then um Okay. So this
is hard. Okay. But I want you guys to
imagine this. It's really hard. But
what's happened is
the brother says you either surrender
Vicarda or I will cut off our mother's
head. Carter is like fine I surrender.
What happens to the friend now?
>> Yeah. I think he'll feel
>> I think he'll feel really bad about it
and maybe just like can he withdraw from
the vow and be like release you from the
vow.
>> I think if you're that friend it's very
hard to go through the marriage, right?
>> Yes.
>> Because what does a friend want to do?
>> At first he just wanted to get married
but now he's
>> But why do you want to get married?
>> Uh
for alliance. Yeah.
>> For power, right?
Okay. So, so if you are a person
hellbent on power and you see the
scenario, you're like, "Screw this. I'm
not getting married." Why would you do
that?
>> Because you're not gaining power. You're
losing.
>> You're losing all the power. Why?
>> Not just that, but it's like you're
breaking that family apart, I guess.
Yeah. You're not actually forming the
alliance that you want.
>> What the think of you?
>> Uh, the mother slayer.
>> Yes. And what would what do your
soldiers think of you?
>> Yeah. Do you understand?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So, it's really interesting how if
you use your imagination, intuition, you
just play this out.
>> Okay.
Yeah.
>> But does the friend have a moral
obligation to not go through with this?
Like is it would it be moral of them to
do?
>> Right. So that this is a moral dilemma,
right? because they they've already made
a vow to each other that if we win this
battle then I will marry Picarda, right?
Okay. So, so this is the point here. The
point is nothing in life is as simple as
it seems. There's complexity.
Okay. And this is a question like given
this hard choice,
what do you believe to be right choice
and and how do you come to this choice
and what Dante is saying is just your
faith in God will lead you to the right
choice. Right? So Parna cannot possibly
math out what's going to happen. So
particard is like I know it is wrong for
me to break my vow to God and if I break
this vow to God it is worse than my own
life. Okay. So that's her faith. And the
brother's like, "No, I've already made
this promise to my friend before God. I
cannot break this vow and therefore I
have no choice but to up the ante,
right? To gamble basically. He's not
going to he's not really going to kill
his mother, right?"
And Picarda knows in this situation
where my mother's life is being
threatened, I have no choice but to
surrender because obviously my brother
is so power hungry. He's he's he's
willing to destroy the whole world,
right? And when this happens, then God
intervenes
and
implants ideas into people. And the
friend's like, "Screw this. This stuff
is crazy. I probably don't want to get
involved." All right, you understand?
So the idea that Dante's the idea that
this thought experiment shows us is
you can never ever truly strategize. You
can never ever truly math things out.
Okay? The your best guide is your
intuition. Your best guide is your faith
and your will. And then things will
naturally
manifest the way you want them to
manifest. Okay. Uh yes.
Um does that mean so does that mean that
if as long as you have the faith in you
uh whatever you do um the god will lead
you to the result.
Okay. As long as you have faith,
God will give you what you want.
>> As long as you have the faith in you, um
uh the the things you do and uh the God
God will lead you to the right answer.
Um okay. So
in Dante in life there are no easy
answers. Okay? If I were to say to you
have faith in God everything will work
out that's irresponsible.
That's the wrong way to to perceive
things.
Okay. The major idea is that the world
is extremely complex
and
often in life it's better to trust your
intuition than to trust your logic.
Okay, does that make sense?
Your intuition comes from
your connection to God
which is an expression of your faith in
God. Okay. Okay. So when you say have
faith in God, what it's really saying is
have faith in yourself. Have faith in
your intuition. Do what you believe is
right.
>> Okay.
>> Uh yes.
>> Since we're on the topic of
hypotheticals, I would like to know if
it's possible to be put into a situation
where you have to betray a vow you made
to God because you love God. So for
example, say there is this monk who
swore never to kill anyone. And right
there there is a man uh who is
invincible to everyone except the monk.
Like you know how hypotheticals work by
this point and he's about to push a
button that would destroy God. So what
would you do as a monk? You love God so
much you don't want God to be destroyed.
So you kill the man and you break your
vow. Is a situation like this possible?
Okay.
So the answer to this is
what do you think is the right thing to
do?
>> Oh yeah. So my question also just like
her you know I think our people have
their own perspective. You can believe
your own god. I believe my god but is
there possibility that god is almighty
god? It means that it is truth. Everyone
just for looking forward to the one
truth or is this people have their own
you know imagination. So this is my
question. So is there kind of almighty
god there or just the god which is our
existing in individually you know.
>> Okay. So in divine comedy um the god
that presented is not the god of the
bible. It's not the god that you know.
Okay. This is it. This is in um platonic
philosophy what is called the monad. the
source, the center, okay, the soul of
the universe. We will go into what this
God is later on. Okay. Okay. So,
[clears throat] I'm not Okay. So, what's
really important is to appreciate that
great poetry excites the imagination.
Okay. It raises questions for us to
ponder
and whatever problem arises ultimately
you can't say hey what would you know uh
my parent want me to do what would the
Catholic Church want me to do you have
to look inside your heart and ask
yourself what does my heart want me to
do and that's often in life your best
guide to the answer.
Okay, does that make sense, guys?
>> Yeah.
>> So, a follow-up question. Since you said
in relation to my hypothetical that you
should act as what you think to be
right, then we assume that the monk
acted in what he thinks is right and he
killed the man betraying his vow.
However, because he act in the way that
he thinks is right, he still has the
most of God in him and he went to the
uppermost layer of heaven. Let's say
that. So, what you are saying right now
is Picarda's actions don't matter that
much. She only has to forgive herself
and rationalize her actions because if
she rationalizes her actions as an act
of love to God, then she would be able
to ascend beyond her lowest sphere. Is
that what you're saying? Okay. So there
is a fundamental um error in your logic
and the fundamental error is that it is
up to us to be able to rationalize away
our sins.
Okay, that's what what you're assuming.
We have the power to think away
[clears throat] what we've done or
rationalize away what we've done. Okay.
And um we don't
and it's hard it's a hard concept to
understand okay because you think that
okay [clears throat]
these people in history um who've killed
millions of people like Stalin people
like Hitler people like Gen Khan right
well logically they did what they did
because they felt it was right.
I have to save my people. I have to uh
make my people happy and I that's why I
need to start these wars. Okay, that's
what we think they think.
But what if you study literature, what
you recognize is
that there are many different dimensions
to the soul. Okay? And maybe on the
surface you can lie to yourself, but in
your heart, in your true self, you know
exactly what the truth is.
Okay.
Okay. So like because you're using
logic, you're using philosophy and
sometimes it doesn't get you anywhere.
So, so, so, um, I will leave you with
this idea, which is, do you know what
happens
when people take psychedelics or when
they have near-death experiences
or they do meditation? Do you know what
happens? Okay. The thing that happens
is
you are able to a central level where
you're able to see yourself
from the lens of the person you've hurt.
Does that make sense?
You're able to see
when you die or you're near death the
totality of the pain you've caused the
world.
Okay, it's pretty amazing. But people
who take who who do psychedelics I aska
um people who have near-death
experiences they all say this when this
happens to you when when you actually
ascend when you leave your corporal body
the first thing that happens is
something called a life review where
you're able to see once and for all the
totality of the pain you've caused other
people. Even that cat you kicked. Okay.
You you you you can see it and you're
like, "Wait a minute. I don't even
remember I kicked a cat." No, you're
able to see it. Okay.
All right. Does that make sense? So,
just because you think something doesn't
mean it's all you're able to think.
Okay.
>> Wait, professor. So, that So, does Do
you mean that like if I meditate enough
like I'll be able to kind of like
foresee the future and see who will win
like the 26 World Club cup or something
like
>> I I never said that.
>> Uh uh professor uh do you mean that it's
kind of butterfly effects? It means that
I do something but I don't mean to to to
do something for for other people. For
example, maybe I just fell in love with
a girl but I don't know there's another
girl who doesn't love me too. So it's
it's got to hurt. Is that all right? So,
so let me rephrase it in a way, okay?
Um, is
everything you do is being recorded by
the universe. There is an eternal memory
of you do in the universe. And this
eternal memory is stored inside you as
well. And even though you don't know
this, even though you don't remember
anything,
when you die, after you die, this
eternal memory will be revealed to you
in its totality. The question for you
is,
do you want to when you actually see
this all this recording of your life and
you see all the pain you've caused other
people,
do you want to deal with that? Okay.
And this is a truth that's embedded in
all religions
and this is something that is also uh
embedded in divine comedy. All right? So
this is something that we will discuss
later on. But I want you to remember
this idea. Everything you you do you do
first of all it's being recorded in by
the universe. Second of all everything
you do impacts the universe in a certain
way.
Okay. So if you live a good life this
brings happiness to universe. If you
live a bad life it brings sadness to
universe.
>> Sorry I have questions. So I curious
about the relationship between this kind
of memories and uh physical materials
that matters.
>> Where's your memory stored?
>> Uh physical material.
>> Yeah. Where's your memory stored?
>> So in brain.
>> Are you sure?
>> Uh uh I I am pretty sure.
>> Have you have you talked to a
neuroscientist?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Actually I choose a
philosophy of cognitive science.
>> Okay. Someone Google for me
what evidence do we have that memories
are stored inside the human brain. We
have nothing. Google it for me. Yeah. Go
ahead. Uh um
evidence that the memories are stored
inside the brain.
>> Great. Can you just read it, Carol?
>> Uh okay. Um memories
Memories are not video recordings stored
in a single file. Instead, they're
encoded by altering the physical
connection signapse between neurons.
When you learn something new, neurons
form stronger or newer connections
through a process called long-term
potentiation.
Um, anyway, NIH researchers uncover how
the human brains separate da da da.
Where are memories stored in the brain?
Memories aren't stored in just one part
of brain. Different types are stored
across different [clears throat]
>> we don't know. Okay. This is all sonic
garbage for like we don't know. Most
basic question is like where are your
memories stored? We don't know.
>> Yeah.
>> Um technically we do know. Uh so uh um
so there's this very famous case of this
person called HM. he had his hippocampus
was um damaged and so he no longer had
long-term memory. And so to some extent
through animal um psych experiments we
can understand that memories at least
the function of memory is supported by
the hippocampus in uh relation with the
cortex.
>> Okay. So that example, that case study
shows us that he cannot access long-term
memory. Does that make sense? It does
not prove that he no longer has
long-term memory. It just means he lacks
access to his long-term memory,
right?
>> Um it's that he was not able to form
long-term memories. And
>> no, but but I'm saying like how do you
know for sure he's not able to form
long-term memory? It shows us he cannot
access long-term memory. And it could be
because he cannot form long-term memory.
It could also mean that there's there's
a disconnection between his long-term
memory and his consciousness.
>> Right?
>> So, so I have further questions like if
if we assumes that the memory is not
stored in brain, so what's the physical
realizers of memory or if memory don't
uh naturally needs just physical
realizers? So, what's the relationship
between uh memories and phys physical
materials?
>> Okay. So um there have been recent neuro
neurosic studies that
um argue that our memory our
consciousness is stored inside the
universe. Okay. So think of the internet
and our brains are just um smartphones
that access the internet. So our
memories are stored on the cloud and
what our brains do is it access the the
cloud. Uh yes. Uh but how would you
possibly explain the fact that um say a
person who can um form long-term memory
before but he's getting older and older
and he got um a part of his hippoc
campus degraded and then he forgot a lot
of things. He even forgot who who he was
and how could you explain how
hippocampus like a specific region in
your brain is not related to your
memory.
>> So you have a computer right? When you
buy the computer the internet connection
is very smooth. You can download things
really fast, right? Over time, as you as
you use it more and more, the connection
becomes worse and worse because it's an
old computer.
>> It's the hard like the hard drive in the
computer was um broken or like just with
war with time,
>> right? And there are different types of
memory, right? There's memory you can
store in your computer. There are
memories you can store on the cloud.
There are memories you can access
through other parts,
right?
And I want to add up to the the
psychedelic question you you raised
before. So um it's a chemical um
compound that actually I I study
neuroscience in college. I like it
actually hits a certain receptor in your
brain that cause like a down um downward
signaling effect that u makes you
meditate, makes you trip and all that.
And this is a very physical or like
chemical thing. Uh but now you said the
memory is not about this uh material
thing um but rather related to the the
universe or um some more spiritual kind
of realms. Um how would you explain the
differences?
>> Okay. So first of all there different
psych psychedelics
right and what is interesting is
depending on on a psychedelic you'll
have different experiences. So, for
example, if you're on Awasa, you'll see
like demons and spirits floating around
you,
>> like the entities. Yeah, I've heard of
that. Um, but the majority of um
psychedelics, they they actually hits
the similar regions or like at least the
like maybe they share 70% the same like
5HT2A receptors in your brain. That's
the the serotonin thing it hits. And if
yeah there are lots of differences like
psilocybin like LSD and all that but um
the effects are more similar than
they're different would you agree okay
so again what's happening is that you're
looking at the at the hardware issues
and you completely ignore the software
does that make sense you're like okay
okay this connection this fiber optic
connection um you are analyzing it and
detailing it how it works. But who
cares? What what what matters is the
information you're downloading. Why are
you able to download certain information
when you take a certain psychedelic?
>> And the argument is that
>> our brains exist in order to anchor
ourselves to this material world. We
have to believe that this material world
is what's real. Because if you just do
if you if your brain just can do
whatever it wants. It's able to access
all the information on the internet, the
computer going to explode, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So your computer has to be strategic
about what information it um absorbs in
order to navigate the world, right?
Ultimately, you just have to survive.
You have to you have to like get food.
You have to like get along with other
people. You have to have sex. You don't
have children, right?
>> Yeah. And this is what Yeah. So the so
so the the your brain is strategic in
how it absorbs information and then how
it actually perceives this information.
>> Yes.
>> We're say it filters out a lot of
information. But when it
>> filters out 99% of all information.
>> Yeah. And when you take psychedelics, it
actually like reopen the gate of
receiving more information.
>> And so you're now able to see all these
different forces at work including
spiritual forces
>> and also when your ego is shut shutting
down.
>> Right. Exactly. Yeah. And so your ego
shut down and so you're able to see it
from more objective lens. Okay. Does
that make sense?
>> So that that you would say is actually
more objective.
>> Okay. The point I will make is that the
period we're living in today in the year
2026 in China, it is a unique period in
human history. We go back to most of
human history. Okay.
Most cultures were animistic,
shamanistic, meaning it was just assumed
that there were ghosts and spirits all
around you.
>> Yeah. Like trees have spirits and
animals have spirits, but now we just
use that as resources for our own needs,
>> right? Do you understand? It's just
weird to me how for the vast majority of
human history, we just assumed that the
universe is conscious, that there is a
god, that there are spirits all around
us. They manip and these spirits
manipulate us. Okay? And like for the
past 50 years, we're like, "No, it's
just us and that's it." And we don't we
don't know how consciousness works. We
have absolutely no idea where memories
are stored.
Uh yes.
Uh I want to add a comment. So if the
brain uh if the memory is stored in the
hardware is stored in the brain as a
hardware um there should be a upper
limit. But actually there's not a upper
limit.
>> Exactly. So we cannot possibly explain
how we're able to have have these
conversations, right? Like if in fact
that the brain is like a computer and
there are synapses,
then there should be a limit to the
storage of the memory, right? But we
know for a fact that there are certain
people who can memorize Paradise Lost
and recite it. There are people who can
memorize divine comm and recite it.
>> Excuse me.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. And and then we also know the
human brain is able to take tremendous
leaps of imagination which if if it were
to translate into a computer would
require like entire worlds of computer
that processing power in order to make
the imaginary leaps that we make.
>> Right? That's why I think a full
reductionist view of the human brain and
the the relationship between the
physical and spiritual is is um um not
not ideal because yeah we I I mean I
study neuroscience. I know uh like the
something about the brain but but like
we still cannot just um just like give
up the the spiritual part about it.
>> So so again I go back to divine comedy.
Okay.
If God doesn't exist, I have no idea how
this was written.
If God does not exist, I don't know how
this was written. I just don't. How
could one man over the course of 20
years without any computers by himself?
Okay? Like literally by himself in his
room, he's able to conceive all this.
And then
almost a thousand thousand thousand
years later we're able to sit down
together and read it and understand
completely what he's trying to convey
and not only that but we find what he's
trying to convey beautiful and truthful.
How does that work? Uh, professor uh is
is that possible that this just like
people right now just get smoking, get
drinking, the nicing or even the you
know marijuana which just can inspire
people to get a high so that they can
make you good use of their brain for
more than other people. Maybe normal
people they got only have 30% of their
brain but he can just make use of about
100% or maybe is it possible?
>> Okay. All right. So, um
I mean the reality is that we don't have
a Dante in this age when we have access
to all the world's information
when we have unlimited wealth.
I mean, compared to
Dante, we're all kind of stupid. I I
don't understand how this works.
Okay. All right. So, so let's let's
continue the divine comedy. Okay, one
one last comment and then we'll continue
the binding comment. Okay.
>> So, I think uh in this discussion I
think it's really important to separate
the inside from the outside. So, if
you're talking about the inside, if
you're talking about the literary genius
of the divine comedy, then I absolutely
agree with what you said. I think it's
an amazing work and I think if you're
talking about God in the context of the
divine comedy, then I absolutely agree
with everything you said about divine
inspiration. However, if you're going to
take this to a outside, if you're going
to take this to our present day, if
you're going to take this to our brains,
our neuroplast plasticity, then I have
to say that I am not convinced by your
arguments because I personally do not
believe in God and because many others
do not believe in God. And I think it's
kind of it's kind of weird that we're
trying to take an argument from divine
comedy outside into our present day
science.
Okay. So, this is a class um of
speculation, of inquiry, of debate.
Okay. So, um you can believe whatever
you want. All right. Anyway, let let's
continue. Okay. Uh Carol, could you
continue to read, please?
>> Sure. Um we're picking up at KTO 5, line
43.
Um paradigm.
Two things are of the essence when one
bows a sacrifice. The matter the matter
of the pledge and then the formal
compact one accept
this last can never be annoyled until
the compact is fulfilled. It is of this
that I have spoken to you so precisely.
Therefore, the Hebrews found it
necessary to bring their offering.
Although, as you must know, some of
their offerings might be altered. As for
the matter of the vow discussed above,
it may be such that if one shifts to
other matter, one commits no sin. But
let but let none shift the burden on his
shoulder through his own judgment.
without waiting for the turning of the
white and yellow keys. And let him see
that any change is senseless unless the
thing one sets aside can be contained in
one's new weight as four and six.
Thus, when the matter of a vow has so
much weight and worth that tip every
scale, no other weight can serve as
substitute.
>> Okay. So, the idea here is that take
your vows seriously. So uh in her book
the human condition Hannah Rand said
that there are two actions okay that
make us fundamentally human. There are
two things that we do that we can all do
that make us fundamentally human. The
first is to make promises.
Okay? Because when you make promises
what you're doing is you're bonding
yourself to another person but you're
also bonding yourself to the future. You
are imagining together a future. Okay,
does that make sense? So making promises
is a very very serious thing that only
humans can do and which expresses our
humanity. But then there's another thing
that we do that makes us fully human and
which expresses our human humanity. Do
you guys know what it is? Number one is
to make promises. What what's the other?
H
breaking promise is not a good thing.
But but that's half the answer.
Swear.
>> Huh?
>> Swear.
>> That's That's making a promise.
>> What's the other thing that makes us
truly human? Which expression our
humanity which uplifts our humanity?
>> H
>> language speaking.
>> Love.
>> Animals can speak.
>> Animals can love.
>> Gratitude,
>> art, and imagination.
Uh, no. What?
>> Yeah. I I would have said to create
things.
>> No, there's there's something else
that's that makes us uniquely human.
>> Self reflection.
>> Self-reflection.
Yeah.
>> Maybe language like a development.
>> An action, guys. Think of an action that
you do with people, not by yourself, but
with other people. The first make
promises, right? Making promises to
affirm your individuality with another
person and to imagine a better future.
Maybe to lie,
but it doesn't uplift, but it's
something that humans
>> Yeah. lying is a bad thing.
>> Something that is truly divine that we
that we can do.
>> Can I say?
>> Yes.
>> Sacrifice.
>> Uh sacrifice.
What do you mean by that?
>> Um
the giving of oneself
for another person's good but
inconveniencing and potentially hurting
oneself.
>> Okay.
All right, that's close. But it's it's
actually much more spec specific than
that. Okay.
>> Okay.
>> Good.
>> Okay. All right. All right. It I mean
it's something that happens every day,
right? So, for example,
um we're walking on the streets. Okay. I
don't see you. I'm I'm really walking
really fast. So, I bump into you and you
fall down, right? And I say, "I'm
sorry." You apologize.
>> Okay. And you forgive. Do you
understand? These are the two things
that makes us truly human to make
promises and to forgive each other for
breaking promises or for making
mistakes. Okay. So this is a really
important idea because you ask yourself
what makes a good society?
What makes a just and happy society? And
it's these two things. If people feel
empowered to make promises
and if people feel empowered to forgive
each other because often guys it's hard
to forgive each other then this is a
good just moral divine society. Okay.
Does that make sense? All right. So
um we as humans should strive to create
a society in which we can make promises
and we can forgive each other. Okay. All
right. Um
so making promise is a very big thing
and what diet is saying is that
sometimes you make a promise that is so
valuable that you can never compensate
for it. Okay. And the example she uses
Picarda makes a promise to God. Okay.
And there's something she could do to
compensate for this.
But she also recognizes that
nothing in the universe is absolute.
And so she's going to
um explain that the situation is much
more complex than we think. Okay. Can
you can you can you continue can you
read please?
>> Sure. Um Paradise Kanto 5 line 64.
Let mortals never take a vow in Jeff. Be
faithful and yet circumspect, not rash
as Jeepa was in offering his first gift.
He should have said, "I did a miss and
not done worse by keeping faith."
>> Okay. Okay. This is really interesting.
Okay. Does anyone know who Jetpa is?
Okay. All right. So, let me tell the
story of Jetpa. This is in the Bible and
it's in the book of Judges. Okay. And
Jetpa, he's he's obviously a leader of
the Israelites. Okay. A leader of the
Israelites. And he goes to war. He goes
to battle and he says, "Dear God, I
swear to you, if I win this battle, if
you let me win this battle, I will give
you as an offering the first person to
walk in my door." Okay? Right.
He's made this vow to God and according
to Beatress, if you make this vow to
God, you must keep it. Who's the first
person? So, he wins this battle. Okay.
And who's the first person that walks in
the door in his house? You guys know?
>> His daughter.
>> His daughter. He's completely screwed
now, right? So, what does he do
according to the Bible?
>> Well, yeah. She he kills the daughter.
Okay.
According to Petri, is this good or bad?
No, it's not a gray area. What did she
say?
What What did she literally say?
And
>> and what
>> you should have said, I did a miss and
not done worse by keeping faith.
>> He should have broken the vow.
She said, "W make that vow, man. I don't
care if you make that vow to God. If you
have to kill your daughter,
don't keep that vow, man. So, this is a
paradox, right? Someone someone help me
understand this paradox.
It would seem that
like Viet Picarda has ended up in the
bottom level of heaven because she's
she had fear in her vow. So, she didn't
she didn't complete her vow with 100%
total faith. And so, here he's he's
putting himself in in some sort of lower
level or even maybe out of heaven. I'm
not sure. But he's never going to get
the higher levels of heaven because he's
he's not taking his vow seriously. But
it was a vow that he could never
>> commit. Who?
>> Um it seems to be Jebid. What's
>> No, no, no. So, Jeba is a reference.
Okay. Beatric is talking and she she's
explaining to Dante um take your vow
seriously and don't be like Jeffa but
that's a paradox because Jeffa did take
his vow seriously
right so someone explain to me the the
the the reasoning here
do you understand it's a paradox she
said take your vows seriously and don't
be like jeta who did take his vows
seriously uh yes new than than new.
Okay. Yes.
>> I think taking it seriously is
understanding the the weight of the vows
you make that when you make a vow you
you like you know taking vows seriously
and don't simply make the wrong vow and
make the vows in haste.
>> Okay. Yes.
>> Yeah. I agree. It's the same.
>> It doesn't it doesn't help me understand
the paradox here.
>> There's a paradox. Yes. So what I'm
trying to say is I think that God uh God
instituted all of this understanding
into us so that we will be able to
follow his rules. So as I mentioned
before like the first time when we when
we were doing the hypothetical about
Picarda uh I mentioned that if you truly
believe in God then you should truly
respect God's gifts and you should truly
respect God's most precious gift which
is free will. So maybe God instituted
this understanding into us so that we
will be able to not make promises such
as this. It's like it's like prevention.
It's like a vaccine. It's like a
prevention shot. Is that possible?
>> I I still don't understand what you're
trying to say. Explain to me the paradox
where Petra said
take your vow seriously and don't be
like JetBA who took his vows too
seriously. It's a paradox.
Uh no, sorry. We uh you you first.
>> Could this be like a jab at the Catholic
Church?
>> Yeah. Well, everything Donnie does is a
jab at the Catholic Church, but but
yeah, can you explain?
>> Well, just saying that obviously there
was jeter from the from the Bible and
that he obviously followed through with
this vow, but used sort of zero uh
circum circumspect and rationality to
look back and realize that it's wrong.
And maybe at the time of writing a lot
of religious people would have taken
more of that view but he's showing that
you need to sort of have more tact.
>> Okay. Uh yes.
>> Well my answer would be that um Hannah
Erin said that like the first thing is
what makes us human is to make promises
and then the second thing was to forgive
forgive ourselves and this is probably
to forgive ourselves is more important
than making promises. So what Jeffa
should have done is just forgive
himself. Forgive himself for
breaking the promise.
>> Yes, that's right. So that's what
Beatric wants. Like just Jeff, you did
make a promise but you did it in you did
it rashly, right? So just forgive
yourself and not
kill your daughter, man. Yes.
So I think that we should understand
this by looking at like all the three
works of Dante because like I read
Infernal first and I think that in
infernal if you uh commit like treachery
against kin that's not just you know
murder and that's that that that doesn't
mean that you just belong to the seventh
circle. You get put like way lower. Yes.
>> So um I think that this is kind of what
Beatatrice is kind of saying. So like
compared to breaking a vow, like if you
kill your daughter, you're going to end
up like farther away from God, you're
going to end up in hell. While if you
break maybe a promise, you will probably
end up like Picarda. So that is still
much better than ending up in hell.
>> But why is church so bad? Why why why
would be worse than breaking a vow to
God?
I think it's like the violence of it all
and also because they are like your own
flesh and blood.
So, you know, that would be kind of
gruesome.
So,
um so, so let let's do the hypothetical
where okay, the problem is that JetBA
[clears throat]
um had to kill the daughter. Okay, let's
just say,
okay,
the person coming in the door is not the
daughter, but the ant. Now it's okay,
right?
Now it's okay because it's not the
daughter, it's the ant. Let's let's kill
the ant.
>> I think he would if he would kill the
ant then like he would probably still
end up like in the seventh circle or
lower.
>> I think so as well. Okay. So So now it's
like it's not the ant, it's the
neighbor. That's That's okay now, right?
>> No, actually actually in Inferno, if you
kill your neighbor, you also end up
>> Okay, you're still bad. Okay, let's give
you the the daughter. Okay, how about I
don't know, stranger.
>> Yeah, the stranger.
>> That's still murder.
>> That's still So, no matter who he kills,
okay,
he's still going to hell,
right? So, so what's going on here? You
say flesh and blood, but it's not flesh
and blood. And it's not treachery,
especially in this case. He's not.
>> Yeah. But in this case, because it's
flesh and blood, that's why it's so bad.
That's why he is like the key example
that
>> I understand, but I'm saying like, let's
just switch and say it's not the
daughter. Let's just say it's a complete
stranger. Is it okay now?
Okay. All right. Okay. So, this is hard.
Okay. Okay. So, what I'm going to do now
is I'm I'm going to present a
hypothetical.
Okay.
And let's just say
I
um I have a wife and I love my wife.
Okay. My wife says to me, "If you truly
love me,
you will go steal a million dollars from
the bank so I can buy a Porsche."
This is just hypothetical. My my my wife
would never do that.
What's my response now? If you truly
love me, you go and steal a million
dollars from a bank
and buy me a Porsche.
>> Is it possible about the sabotage? I
mean, just you love me, so you have to
do something for me. Is it kind of the
excuse because you want to take control
over you? Is it possible?
>> What is my proper response? My my So,
you're saying my response should be, you
know what? Um,
I'll go rob a bag and buy some jewelry.
is is like what's what's my reput
response?
[laughter]
>> Oh yeah.
>> You wish you say if you really love me
and you you can't force me to to buy for
you buy something for you.
>> Okay. [laughter] Okay. Okay. All right.
All right. Okay. So So this is really
key to understanding D. Okay. So my wife
says to me, if you truly love me, you
will go rob a bank and buy me a Porsche,
right? or go start a business and make a
billion dollars.
And so you think I should go go and make
a billion dollars
to show my wife, show my love, my my
love to my wife.
Does that feel right to you?
What's the right thing for me to to to
do here?
Yeah,
>> because it's to investigate why she
would make such a request and try to get
to the truth of it all.
>> Yeah. So, I ask her like, "Do you really
want me to do it?" Just, "Yes, I really
want you to do it." I'm so stuck. Right.
Maybe just
>> Yeah. Who? Sorry. Who? Who? Who?
>> Okay.
>> Maybe just leave her.
>> I should leave her.
>> Yeah. Because that that does mean that
she doesn't actually love you because
the real love is unconditional.
>> Yeah. Actually, I Yeah. Yeah. It's like
I probably going to hold a similar
opinion. Maybe we just leave her because
uh because like based on the plot's cave
theory like you mentioned in the in the
video and I think if she just cannot
know what happens beyond the mirror then
and we never can wake up a person that
do not want to be awake you know so we
will possibly just leave her and find
someone else that we have the like
similar similar opinion or the similar
uh
I was just saying you'd say no.
>> Yes. Okay. All right. So, all right.
This is hard. Okay. But the right
decision, the right course is just to
walk away from her. Right. Because the
logic is this. If she's making you this
request, like if you truly love me,
go steal me a million dollars, right?
Well, first of all, she doesn't love
you, right? She can't possibly love you
if she's making this request because if
you go rob a bank, they're going to put
you in prison, right? You're not going
to get them. You're not going to go by
the car. You're going to go to prison.
Okay, that's number one. Number two is
if she doesn't love you, right? You
being with her is wrong.
You understand? So, you should just let
her, if you truly love her, you should
just let her go find someone who's right
for her. Does that make sense?
Okay. So, this goes back to this case
where
Zeba is saying, "I love God so much that
I'm willing to give
him my first daughter." And God's like,
"That's not what I want, man. I don't
want this crap from you." You
understand? So what faith is is first
and foremost understanding the nature of
God. You understand? God is first and
foremost love.
And when you kill your daughter,
you it's an act of treachery
which
degrades love in the universe. So you
are not obeying God. You're betraying
God. You understand?
Does that make sense?
If my wife were say, "Go rob a bank to
give me a million dollars." Okay, I have
to say to her, "No,
it's because I love you that I'm not
going to do this. If I go rob the bank,
it's only because I want to possess you.
It's only because I want to control
you." That's an act of betrayal of love.
Okay? Okay. Does that make sense? Okay.
So, the paradox can only be resolved if
you understand that the nature of God is
love itself. And because God is love
itself and because God loves you
unconditionally, God would never
ever ask you to
hurt someone or betray yourself. Does
that make sense?
And so when you make this vow,
I promise you God that if I win this
battle, I will I will kill the first
person who walks in the door.
God's going to ignore you. Okay? Do you
understand? I don't care. No one cares
if you make this promise. God doesn't
care if you make this promise. God's
just going to ignore you because it came
through rashness. It It was because you
don't understand God. Okay? If you don't
understand God and there's no
connection, there's no way you can make
this vow. Yes,
>> that's exactly what I meant what I meant
to say. So, if you truly understand God,
then you would never make such a vow.
It's like a vaccine. God has put it put
us put in us the understanding that we
would not make such a vow. That's the
vaccine to prevent us from something
doing something like this.
>> Okay. Yeah. But then why do people make
make these vows?
>> Because because they have not taken the
vaccine because because they have not
been in contact with God. Therefore,
such a vow is ungodly.
>> How do they break their connection to
God?
>> By understanding themselves more fully.
Like I'm like I said, God made
provisions for us and it's up to us to
discover these provisions. It's up to us
to make ourselves his vessel. Is that
what you're saying?
>> No, no, no. I'm I'm saying like
how did we lose our connection to God?
You're saying we lost our connection to
God, but how do we lose it? Because why
would we why would we lose it? It makes
no It makes no sense.
like because we have free will as you
mentioned before whether or not to lose
our connection to God.
>> How did why did Jeffa make this make
this vow?
Why did Jeffa make this vow?
What's the reason?
>> Yes.
>> I think he was in the really hard to win
battle and he wanted God to really help
him.
>> He wanted power.
>> Yeah.
>> You understand?
>> Yeah. He wanted power and that's what
moved him away from God. You understand?
When you want power, you want worldly
power, that's what severe connection to
God.
You've always had it, but you lose it
when you want power.
Okay.
All right. Can you can you can can you
read uh Carol,
>> can I can I ask before we move on? So
life seems to be fraught with mindfields
of vows that people can make on your
behalf. So we've got Picarda's brother
has made a vow on her behalf. And I
understand she ends up in the bottom
level of heaven essentially because she
had 90% faith instead of 100% faith and
she was a bit fearful. But so Jeepa's
daughter
is uh has this vow essentially bestowed
upon her. And you said that God ignores
vows when they're made
incor incorrectly like like sinfully or
ungodly. I'm getting the wording wrong,
but that there is some connection here
with Carta and her brother because the
vow was made
for for power there as well. and her
place in heaven suffers because of this
whole seemingly situation. So I guess
maybe my my question is getting toward
like
where would Jebza's daughter be in the
hierarchy of would she end up in the
inferno because submitting to her
father's death would be like a form of
suicide?
>> That's a really interesting question.
Yes. Okay. So, um,
sorry. Why would Jeff be inferno and not
in paradise? Do you guys know why?
>> Okay. Yeah. I I your question. Okay. But
like first my first question is, do you
guys know where Jeffa would be in
Inferno? He's actually not. Uh, so where
would Jeff be in in in in in Divine
Comedy? Which which level? Inferno,
purgatory, or
um paradise.
But why Inferno?
>> He killed his daughter.
>> No, he's actually inferno because he's
not a Christian. Okay. Uh he's inferno
because
um he was born before the time of Jesus.
Therefore, he could not become a
Christian. Therefore, he cannot access
heaven. Okay, that's point one. Point
two is
where would Jeff's daughter be? You guys
know
>> purgatory?
>> Why purgatory and not anywhere else?
Um I mean following that logic um has
not known Jesus but um not knowing how
she has acted in her own life. I'm just
assuming that she has not killed anybody
else. And so this is um she was killed
against her presumably
against her own will and even if it's
her will she was the victim.
>> Yes.
Who's the hero of the story?
Who's the hero of the story? If you read
the Bible, who who's the hero of the
story?
>> The daughter.
>> The daughter. But why the daughter?
>> Um because she understands the
importance of the vow. She wants to keep
it despite that she has to sacrifice
herself.
>> Yes. Okay. If you read the Bible, it's
clear the daughter who is the hero of
the story because she was willing to
sacrifice herself to ensure her father
keeps keeps about, right? Because if you
read the Hebrew Bible, the worst thing
you can do is not give your vow to uh
God. Uh so she would actually be in
paradise.
>> Ah
>> okay. Does that make sense? So this is a
this is a paradox of divine comedy where
there's a rule that if you're not a
Christian, you are not you can't be in
paradise. You can only be in purgatory
or in inferno. But because of the
nobility of her sacrifice, she gets
elevated to paradise. Okay.
Right. And so it doesn't logically make
sense, but it makes intuitive sense.
Does that make sense? Yes.
>> Part where you said the sacrifice, the
daughter made a sacrifice.
>> Okay. The story is this. Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> The story is that JetBA to win a a war
because he's leader of the Israelites.
Okay. And the Israelites have lots of
enemies uh because it's the Middle East,
right? And they win this battle. Um, but
before the battle, Jeff says, "If I win
this battle, I swear to God, I will
offer as sacrifice
whoever walks in my door." Okay, he
makes this vow.
He goes home. The first one to walk in
the door is his daughter. Now he's
screwed. Okay, because either you kill
your daughter or you defy God, right? So
he is completely utterly screwed. So
what the daughter says is, "Father,
let me make my own offering. Let me
sacrifice myself willingly so that it
absolves you of the guilt of killing me
and it allows you to fulfill
um your promise to to to
God." And why this is worthy of paradise
is it is an act of love because it is
completely selfless. You understand?
Okay. And when you commit acts of love,
you are elev elevated to uh paradise.
Okay. Is that clear guys?
>> Sorry.
>> So you mean willingness is the necessary
if it can be you know up level into the
paradise?
>> Excuse me. the willingness because you
said you will to die. It means that you
can go to paradise. Is that what you
mean?
>> No. No. I just said a selfless act of
love is what elevates you to paradise.
Not the will, not the desire, but the
action itself that's driven by the will
and the desire. Yes.
>> But there should be acts of love before
Christianity.
>> That's why she's in heaven. She's not a
Christian. She's a Hebrew.
She doesn't believe in Jesus. But if God
could put her anywhere, God would put
her in paradise.
Okay? In fact, when we read, what you
will discover is there are quite a few
pagans in paradise.
Okay? So, this is subversive because the
rule is unless you're a Christian, you
can't go to paradise. You read Divine
Comedy, there are there are some pagans
in paradise. Okay? Does that make sense?
Uh, yes.
>> Isn't offering herself some sort of
suicide and isn't that a sin?
>> Um, yeah. The Catholic Church, uh, for
the Catholic Church, suicide is a sin.
But these are the Hebrews. These are
these are the Israelites. Okay. So, this
is a different cultural context.
And
it's not really uh Yeah. Okay. Does that
make sense? All right. Okay. All
right, let's So, Carol, can we keep on
going?
>> Okay, Paradise KTO 5 um line 67. He
should have said idimus and not done
worse by keeping faith. And you can find
that same stupidity.
>> So, so you see the paradox in in the
sentence, right?
>> Doing worse by keeping faith.
>> How does that make any sense? Right? Am
I going? And you can find that same
stupidity in the Greeks chief when her
faith when her fair faith made Ephenia
grieve and made the wise and made the
foolish weep for her when they heard
tell of such a right.
>> Okay, so this is also a really
interesting story. Okay, so she's saying
that there are two really stupid people
in this world. First is Jetba, the other
is Eggman. Okay, so uh this is Trojan
War and what starts the Trojan War of
course is that Paris of Troy steals
Helen of Sparta
and so Helen is the most beautiful woman
in the world and all the Greeks fight
for Helen and it seems like a war is
about to break out among the Greeks and
so what the Greeks decide to do is you
know what we'll just cast lots and
whoever wins
will marry Helen and everyone else is
obligated
to
fight for Helen if someone seal tries to
steal Helen. Okay, does that make sense?
It's an oath before the gods. And so
Helen marries Manalas uh the brother of
Egenon and the king of Sparta.
Then Paris steals Helen and now the
Greeks are obligated by this oath to go
and destroy Troy. And this what this is
what starts the Trojan War and Agame
Manon is the leader of the Greek army.
So the Greeks assemble this huge fleet
off the um coast of Greece and they're
about to sell the Adriatic and move and
and war against Troy. The problem is
that Agamenon kills like a secret animal
to Artemis, the the the the goddess of
the hunt. And Artemis gets angry and
says, "Screw you. You Greeks aren't
going anywhere." And she destroy she she
so there's no more wind. Okay. So the
Greeks are stuck where they are. So Aman
is like, "No, we need to go to Troy
because of this oath to the gods." And
he talks to a prophet and says, "What
can I do to restore the winds?" And the
prophet says if you kill your daughter
Ephagenia
Artemis will be appeased. Okay.
So the second manon
kills Ephagenia
even though is extremely popular among
the people and it's also like his
daughter.
Okay. So this was
stupid.
And ultimately, if you know the story of
um the uh Greeks,
what happens to to Egon because he
killed Ephagenia? You guys do you guys
know the story?
>> Yeah, I think um if mother Clayton
Mestra
um revenged on a
>> your daughter were killed by your
husband, what did you do? You probably
go kill the guy. Okay. Tamestra plots
this vengeance against Egamenon. And so
when comes home, Famero kills him for
killing Epigenia.
Okay. So
um
um should could have could Eggman have
known this?
Could Eggman have predicted this?
Probably. Okay. So that this is why it's
stupid,
right? Okay. So just I understand it's
important to keep your vows to the gods
but like what is saying is like use your
brains people. Okay.
All right. So Jeffa was stupid. Eggman
was stupid as well. Okay. Keep on
reading. Uh Carol
>> Paradise Kanto 5 line 73.
Christian, proceed with greater gravity.
Do not be like a feather at each wind,
nor think that all immersions wash you
clean. You have both testaments, the old
and new. You have the shepherd of the
church to guide you. You need no more
than this for your salvation.
>> Okay. Um,
what what is she saying here? Okay. What
is she saying here? What she's saying?
Okay. Yes. It's important to keep your
vows to God, but at the same time use
your brain.
And how can you use your brain?
You have both testaments, the old and
the new. You have the shepherd of the
church to guide you. You need no more
than this for your salvation. This is
very subversive. If I'm in the Catholic
Church and I and I hear this, I'm I'm
pissed off. Why?
>> You don't need the priest.
>> You You don't need a priest. But what do
you need?
>> Bible.
>> The Bible. Do you understand? Okay. What
do you are not allowed to do at this
time if you're Catholic?
>> To read the Bible.
>> Read the Bible by yourself. You're not
allowed to do that. And what Donnie is
saying is like, hey, if you really want
to understand what is true, read the
Bible for yourself. Okay. Yes.
>> So, this is something I'm really uh
confused about. So, first you said that
we should follow our intuition because
our intuition comes from God. And then
you said that we should use our brains.
And then you said that we should read
the Bible. However, if we presume that
God is above all of this, if we presume
that God does not need to make himself
manifest in such things as the Bible or
even the Catholic Church, then what is
God? How should we get closer to God?
>> Okay. All right. So, first let's ask a
question. Okay. Have you read the Bible
before? Okay.
What's the problem with reading the
Bible?
There's loads of versions.
>> Excuse me.
>> Loads of versions. Loads and loads.
>> It's pretty complicated, man. So, what's
the only way you can actually read the
Bible?
>> Use your intuition, man. You understand?
Try reading the Bible using logic. Good
luck with that one.
Right.
What What's the contradiction here?
What what Donn is saying is okay. Yes, I
understand that you made the this vow to
God and you want to know what to keep
and what to what to break. Use your
intuition. How? Read the Bible, listen
to the priest. Okay? Once you have these
two elements, go to church, listen to
the priest, read the Bible. Then this
will be the path to your salvation. So
what what he's really saying is use your
own judgment,
use your intuition,
use your faith. Yes.
>> So what you are basically saying here
back to my inside outside metaphor. So
what you're basically saying here is
that we have to use our intuition but
our intuition is not entirely of our own
control because we cannot use our
intuition to forgive ourselves of
everything we have ever done and
therefore our intuition is something
outside of us and therefore God is a
concrete existence somewhere outside of
us.
>> Okay. All right. So let's try to make
this simple. Okay. It might be wrong but
let's try to make it simple. Okay.
Your intuition is ultimately your
connection to the divine to the
universe. Okay? Because like where does
your intuition come from? It comes from
the source.
But there are ways in which to
strengthen this connection. Okay?
Knowledge, reading,
inquiry, debate,
love, faith. Does that make sense? So
live a life of love, faith, inquiry,
pursuit of knowledge and this will
strengthen your intuition.
Because for Dante, science and intuition
are not mutually exclusive. They are
independent. They are codependent. Only
with intuition can you truly be a
scientist.
Does that make sense, guys?
All right. Uh let's let's let's keep on
going.
Um, Paradise Kanto 5 line 79.
If evil greed would summon you
elsewhere, be men and not like sheep
gone mad, so that the Jew who lives
among you not deride you. Do not act
like the foolish wantum lamb that leaves
its mother's milk and heedless wants to
war against and harm its very self.
These words of Beatus I hear
transcribed. And then she turned, her
longing at the full to where the world
is more alive with light. Her silence
and the change in her appearance imposed
a silence on my avid mind which now was
ready to address new questions. And even
as an arrow that has struck the mark
before the bow cord comes to rest, so
did we race to reach the second realm.
When she had passed into that heaven's
light, I saw my lady filled with so much
gladness that at her joy the planet grew
more bright. And if the planet changed
and smiled, what then did I, who by my
very nature am given to every sort of
change, become as in a fish pool that is
calm and clear. The fish draw close to
anything that nears from outside, if it
seems to be their fair. Such were the
far more than a thousand splenders I saw
approaching us. And each declared, "Here
now is one who will increase our loves."
And even as each shade approached, one
saw, because of the bright radiance it
set forth, the joyous with which that
shade was filled. Consider reader what
your misery and need to know still more
would be [snorts] if at this point what
I began did not go on. And you will
uninassisted feel how I longed so to
hear those shades narrate their state as
soon as they appeared before my eyes. Oh
you born unto gladness whom God's grace
allows to see the thrones of eternal
triumph before your war of life is
ended. The light that kindles us is that
same light which spreads through all of
heaven. Thus he would know us. Say
yourself as you may please. So did one
of those pious spirits speak to me. And
Beatatrice then urged, "Speak. Speak
confidently. Trust them as you trust
God." I see plainly how you have nested
in your own light. See, you draw it from
your eyes, because it glistens even as
you smile. But I do not know who you are
or why, good soul. Your rank is in a
sphere concealed from mortals by another
planet's ray. I said this as I stood
turned toward the light that first
addressed me. And at this it glowed more
radiantly than it had before. Just as
the sun, when heat has worn away thick
mist that moderate its rays, conceals
itself from sight through an excess of
light. So did that holy form through
excess gladness concealed himself from
me within his rays.
And so concealed concealed he answered
me even as the next KTO is to sing.
>> Okay. All right. So what's happening of
course is that Dian Futures are
traveling through the cosmos. They're
going from spear to spear. They are now
in a new spear and the person they meet
is Justinian. Justinian
uh was emperor of the Bison empire.
Okay. the probably the greatest emperor
of the Bian Empire and he will now talk
about the history of Rome which we'll
read the next kanto
um
question there's a word here that
shouldn't be in the divine comm
weird word if you are a Christian if
you're a practicing Christian you hear
this word and you basically
shudder
you you're like what? Okay. It's like
it's it's like basically someone hitting
you. What is this word? The word doesn't
really belong and it should not be here.
There's a word four letters, guys.
Four letter word that should not be in
in
heaven.
It makes absolutely no sense.
H
what? What's the word?
Holy.
>> Holy. No. Holy is a word that you would
want in heaven. Yes. Born.
>> Huh?
>> Born.
No. There's a word that's like what is
it doing here in heaven? You're like
this is wrong.
All right. So it is
to me.
Yes. Thank you. God, what is going on
here?
You guys understand this?
Yeah. You're like you're a Christian.
There's one God.
And it is secular to say there is
another god. There can only be one god.
What is she say? Peter says speak
confidently trust them as you trust god.
Peter says to Justinian talk to Dante.
Speak the truth. Talk
to them
as you trust God.
It's a really strange
word, right?
Does the gods here refer to like the
Greek gods? I mean, I think yesterday we
talked about how at the beginning of the
contos like Dante prayed to, for
example, the Apollo and the Muses even
though he was like Christian.
>> Yeah. Well, I mean like that that can
only be the that can only be the
reference, right? Because Christianity
is monotheistic, meaning just one God.
The Greeks are polytheistic, meaning
many gods, right?
So, so the idea I'm trying to convey is
that there's a subversive quality
[clears throat]
subversive quality
to divine comedy. You can choose to just
read it like as a Christian text. And
quite honestly, most people do read it
as Christian text. And in the ne and I
point this out because in the next conto
we will for Justinian read the entire
history of the Catholic Church. Okay
from its beginnings in Rome to
uh the Holy Roman Empire. Okay. And that
is the official chronology as presented
by the Catholic Church. But what I'm
trying to show you is that there are
small things
embedded throughout the text that
subvert the traditional understanding of
Christianity.
It doesn't make sense, guys. And unless
you read it deeply,
you can't actually appreciate it. Uh
yes,
>> we see this as a humanistic perspective.
Like uh we often say uh modern day
celebrities are called stars, right? And
sometimes we say gods of the literary
cannon and sometimes we almost worship
the greats in our history. And can this
be seen as this pioneer of the
humanistic perspective that uh humans
can be great in and of themselves even
those who are not great through religion
like pagans, like Archimedes.
>> Exactly. Okay. And and what what you say
is the Renaissance. Okay. What makes the
Renaissance a revolution in human
affairs is that as you say um it uh
celebrates the human spirit and how the
human spirit can be a force for
innovation and good in the universe and
this is unique in Europe at this time.
Okay. And it starts with Dante. It is
Dante that launches the Renaissance as
well as modernity. It is Dante that
promotes the idea of the individual that
we take for granted today but which was
revolutionary back in his time. Okay.
So, so yes. All right. Um so, um we have
another 20 minutes but um I want to
talk about some ideas. Okay. So
I don't want to give you the impression
that our discussion is the end all and
be all that we've uncovered the truth. I
want to go over into the limitations of
a discussion. Okay. The first limitation
as you can appreciate is
this is written in Italian.
We are reading in English because we
don't speak Italian. This is a severe
limitation because it prevents us from
doing literary analysis. We can't study
the words. We can't study the diction,
the syntax. Okay? And so it limits our
true understanding of what Dante is
trying to convey. It doesn't make sense.
Unless you read this in Italian, it's
impossible to truly decipher his
meaning. That's important. And we've
invited someone Italian to come u read
some passages for us later in the
workshop.
>> Yeah. And that and that'd be great. But
but the point I make is like unless you
read it in Italian by yourself,
>> you'll never truly understand it. Okay.
>> Okay. That's point one. Point two is
that
uh we discussed this before but in the
line there's a lot of numerology and
mathematics because you think about it
for Dante mathematics is the underlying
truth of the universe. Okay, mathematics
numerology is what provides the
structure of the universe and there's a
lot of actually numerology and
mathematics within the divine comedy.
The most basic example is a structure
where it's 34 ktos in inferno, 33 in
purgatory and 33 in um uh paradise. And
also like if you look at the structure
of the poem, it's three lines by three
lines by three lines. Okay, there's
clearly a numerological significance to
number three because of what?
When you think three, what do you think?
>> Trinity.
>> The trinity. Okay, do you understand?
Okay. So what Dante is doing is he is
using mathematics in order to portray
the divine structure of the universe to
express its intent sorry its
intentionality. Okay, its design. Okay.
So unless you really study the
mathematics, it's again hard to
understand the divine comedy. We're not
going to do that because a lot of
mathemat mathematics is in Italian.
Okay. Mata mthematics would also include
syllables and the rhymes and all that.
Okay. So, we can't do the numerology as
well. The third thing that we're missing
that's very important for divine harmony
is astrology.
Okay.
So, at this time in history, astrology
is science, right? You think that the
movement of stars will determine the
course of events. And if you read Divine
Comedy, if you you look at paradise,
obviously there's a lot of astrology
here, okay? Obviously, the way that the
stars have positioned, the way that D is
looking at the stars from a certain
angle, it's all significant, but I don't
understand any of this stuff. Okay?
So, astrology is also very key. Then you
have
uh the symbology.
So we looked at certain symbols last
class. For example, the four circles and
the three crosses and we pointed out how
you can have lots of rich discussions
over the meaning of these symbols. There
are lots of symbols scattered throughout
divine comedy and obviously there's a
lot of deep meaning uh under these
symbols but unless you actually study
symbology you don't know what they are.
Okay. Um, what what Don is doing that's
very important is that he's combining
different traditions together, right?
Not just the Christian tradition, but
also the pagan tradition, also the um
Islamic tradition,
uh the Gnostic tradition. There's all
sorts of traditions that he's combined
together in order to create the
symbology
uh the im imagery that underlies the
divine comedy. Okay. And the last
element that we can't look at is the
occult. Okay.
The occult
esoterism.
What is the occult? The occult is
basically talking to demons and angels.
Okay? And if you actually know the
occult, you will understand there's a
lot of occult symbolism, a lot of occult
references into the Dying Comedy. I
don't know these references so I cannot
bring them out. Uh yes.
>> Um personally based on my understanding
I would argue that the original meaning
of the word oult is actually the hidden
and the oult can refer to more than
angels and demons. In fact if we're
referring to that we often refer to them
using uh for example demonology. So the
oult can also refer to other topics.
>> Yeah. Right. The cult just means what's
hidden from us or what is esoteric.
Okay. Yes. Um but but most people refer
to it as just talking to demons and
angels. Okay. Um and clearly
Donna spends a lot of time talking to do
to demons and angels, right? So all so
um and and the last thing I would say is
just magic.
Okay. Magic
uh manifestation.
So why I bring this out is like there is
an entire universe
in the divine comedy we cannot access
because of limitations of our language
because of limitations of our knowledge.
So um even though you know we're having
these rich discussions appreciate that
it's only a small fragment of the
entirety of the divine comedy and the
entire purpose of this class is to
encourage you to spend your entire
lifetime
studying the divine comedy. There's
about 20 of you in this classroom. I
guarantee you if you would to spend the
next 50 years studying divine comedy,
each and every one of you would have a
radically different interpretation
of divine comedy because some of you may
learn Italian and go study numerology.
Some of you may learn learn Italian and
go study symbology. Okay? In which case
you present a radically different
conception of the um
of your understanding. Another way of
saying this is
The divine comedy what it really is is
the secret bible of humanity right the
bible is the major religious text for
most people in this world but if you are
an intellectual if you are an inspiring
uh writer the divine comedy is
um what will guide you in your
imaginations okay if you read the divine
comedy throughout the entire life I
guarantee you you're going to be one of
our greatest intellectuals, one of our
greatest writers, greatest thinkers
because there's so much richness. Um,
also like if you actually read the
divine comedy and you study things like
the Cabala, you can you know the Cabala
comes from Divine Comedy. Okay, this is
something that that we might discuss
later on, but the Jewish Cabala
is basically inspired by divine comedy.
something that people don't rec
recognize. But if you're a really smart
person, you're really interested in the
esoteric, in the occult, in magic, in
God, then the divine comedy is the best
source material that you can have. Okay.
And again,
um I I am just amazed at the level of
accomplishment.
I mean it is I think certainly the
greatest individual human achievement
in history far greater than um Einstein
or Newton. But also I think that if we
were to rank Divine Comedy to other
great achievements, okay, the pyramids,
the nuclear bomb, the computer,
whatever, I still think the Divine
Comedy is superior. Okay, that that's my
own uh feeling. Um also I I will um say
that because I have access to all this
okay the six things I'm missing my for
my capacity to fully analyze divine
comedy it also means we'll probably skip
certain sections okay does that make
sense because certain sections are heavy
into the cold astrology and mathematics
and there's really no point for us to
read it because like I don't understand
what's going on right
okay so any questions about this yes
>> do you remember the first time you read
divine comedy and how it felt like and
what
>> yeah I I had no idea what I was reading.
I mean I I I I I started reading Divine
Comedy about four years ago for the
first time. I I didn't read this at
Yale. Um um you I think you have to take
Italian to read Divine Comedy. I I can't
remember. Um and for the for like many
many months I
didn't understand anything. Okay. Like I
would read the words like I don't
understand what's going on. Okay. I
would watch videos. I would I think I
watch like 100 video 100 hours of of
like videos explaining to me what divine
comedy is. It made me even more
confused. Okay. Try try it. Try going on
YouTube. Try watching what these
professors say about divine comedy. It
will just confuse you even more. And so
I'm really really frustrated. But I am I
have to teach this to my students. Okay.
I'm teaching at a high school and I've
taught Homer, I've taught Plato, and I'm
like, I should teach Dante as well. So,
I'm like, oh my god, I'm gonna I am
going to be a complete idiot, okay? But
I really really want to teach this to my
student because I really want to teach
great books.
And then one morning I wake up
and
it felt as though Dante walked in my
dreams and he gave me certain ideas and
he said love. Okay, if you want to
understand the divine comedy, think
about what love is. Think about what the
meaning of love is and that will lead
you to the right path. And then divine
comedy started to like open up to me
like the words started to connect
together. Okay. And and and it goes back
to the idea of picarda where if there's
a will there's a way where
I for like four months felt completely
hopeless like this is impossible. This
is just stupid. I can't understand
what's going on. All these YouTube
videos are making more more confused. I
thought hopeless. But when you really
want it, the universe will respond.
Maybe not the way you expect, maybe not
in the way you want, but it will
respond. It will guide you to the right
path. Okay.
So, it's only a question of will and
desire.
Yes. So something I would like to
comment on something that I noticed and
I think it's interesting but
understandable given its time is that so
in fantasy like in fantasy fiction there
are two types of magic. There's hard
magic and there's soft magic. And hard
magic is when you do something like one
plus one and you expect it to equal two.
And soft magic is when you don't know
what will turn up. Magic just turns up
when it needs to. So I think Dante's
magic, Dante's uh esultterism is closer
to soft magic than hard magic. But it's
already showing the basic signs of hard
magic, which I think is really
interesting because in Catholicism, you
cannot expect God to do anything. So
Catholic magic or miracles is absolutely
soft magic. However, as we evolved, as
the disciplines of uh the Cabala, as the
disciplines of cultism evolved, we
gradually got ourselves some rituals. we
got ritualism and that evolved into hard
magic where we do something and we
expect something to happen.
>> Okay. I I agree with that. Yeah. Um what
I'll also say is that I really think
Divine Comedy is the word of God. It's a
universe speaking through Dante. And
that's why I say it's perfect. Okay.
I've not been able to find a flaw in the
Divine Comedy. I mean like look look at
it beauty of its structure. Look at the
beauty of its language. Look at the look
at the economy of its ideas. Okay, we're
able to take one sentence and have like
hours and hours of discussions based on
this. So, um I I I I think it's going to
be worth your while to spend the rest of
your life studying Divine Comedy. It it
is that it is that that good. Um
and um there is magic definitely magic
in this and the more you study the more
you will discover. Okay, I cannot say
this about the Bible. I'm sorry. I've
actually said the Bible it is a complete
mess. Okay, if you actually said the
Bible you're like uh what's going on
here? Um but Divine Comedy, the poetry
makes it perfect, right? Because let's
just say you're in the Middle Ages and
you hear Dante recite poetry, right?
What are you think?
What are you thinking?
It's God, right? It's God taking
possession of Dante and D is reciting
the the poetry. Same thing if you know
you go to a concert and you might have a
favorite musician, but when the musician
is singing, you think it's the universe
singing. It's God that's singing, right?
It touches you that that deeply. All
right. Okay. So, um when we come back
from the break, we will go into the
history of the Catholic Church. Okay. We
first we'll show you the official
history of the Catholic Church and then
we will show I'll show you how Dante
presents a new uh understanding of
um Jesus. Okay. All right. Any
questions?
Okay, guys. So, so I'll see you after
the break. Okay.
What I'm going to do before we read
Dante is I'm going to introduce the
Catholic version of history. Okay. So um
[clears throat]
the end point of history is the Catholic
Church
because the Catholic Church is the
manifestation of God
on earth, right? It is heaven on earth.
So all the events that led Catholic
Church were pre-ordained. They were
intended by God. Okay? And the thing
that starts history and which leads the
Catholic Church is of course Rome.
Rome.
It is God's intention, is God's will
that Rome conquer the world. So it
starts off this very small poor place in
the Italian peninsula. Then it gradually
expands outwards and then it conquers
until it conquers the entire
Mediterranean. Right. It destroys
Carthage, Nethopenic Wars, and now it
controls most of the world, spanning the
Mediterranean from Spain all the way to
Egypt all the way to Syria and the
Levant. Okay? And this is the Roman
Empire. Now, during the course of the
Roman Empire, a civil war breaks out.
Okay?
And of course, Julius Caesar
will win this war, but he will become
assassinated by Brutus and Casius.
And this will lead to the rise of
Augustus Caesar.
And after Caesar dies, Ted Caesar
will come in to power.
And as during the time of emperor of
Caesar, Christianity is born and it
spreads spreading throughout the uh
Roman Empire. It is a miracle because in
the beginning of the first 100 years
it's persecuted. It's a very fringe
religion but by about 300
year 300 it becomes the official
religion of the Roman Empire because of
Constantine
and Constantine
um will decide to shift his capital from
Rome to Conenopole which is modernday
Istanbul and this begins the Bisantine
Empire which is the Eastern
Roman Empire.
And uh the great emperor of the bison
empire is of course Justinian
who we are meeting or who who we have
met in common and Justinian will narrate
the story of the Roman Empire. Okay but
it's basically like this. Now you know
as we know the Roman Empire does split
in half between the western and the
eastern. The eastern empire will fall to
the Turks in the 16th century. um about
a thousand years later, but the Western
Empire falls about the year 400. Okay?
And when it falls, uh Europe is broken
into different kingdoms uh different
factions and about the year 800
uh Charlemagne
uh of the Franks will unite all of
Europe and create something called the
Holy Roman Empire.
Okay. Um,
and the Holy Roman Empire will last
until who do did I tell you history? Who
who destroys Holy Roman Empire?
Excuse me?
No, that's the Roman Empire. Who
destroys the Holy Roman Empire? Did you
guys know your history?
>> Napoleon.
>> Napoleon. Yes. Napoleon Barton. So,
that's a long way. Okay, this is this is
about 18 1800. So the holy empire lasts
for a long long time and from the
perspective of dominant Europeans this
is all the stability the the continuity
it's all because of the will of God.
Okay now over the course of this time as
I said Christianity will develop okay
and Christianity will come to replace
the Holy Roman Empire as the most
powerful force in the world. So it
starts of course with the birth of Jesus
in about 4 BCE. Okay. And then 33 is
when he is crucified and with his death
it will begin the it will begin
Christianity. Uh what will happen is
that Peter will become the first bishop
of Rome. Basically the first pope. Okay.
And then Paul
uh will build the foundations of
Christianity. The I and we'll meet both
Peter and Paul in divine comedy. Not
Jesus but Peter and Paul.
Then what happens is that Christianity
spreads and it becomes official under
Constantine. Okay. So now the Catholic
church is official. Now in about 325
this is something called the council of
Nikia. Nikia is in modern day Turkey but
the council of Nikia is a radical
turning point in Christian history
because before every single place in
Europe had its own distinct church that
blended Christian elements with local
pagan practice.
The council attempt to standize
Christianity by resolving certain
theological conflicts within the church.
Okay. And there are quite a few major
conflicts. The first major conflict is
um the nature of Jesus. [clears throat]
Okay. So, everyone worships Jesus.
That's why you're a Christian. But what
was Jesus? There are some who said that
Jesus was God incarnate, right? There
are some who said Jesus was a man who
was anointed by God to be his messenger.
These are two extremes.
And the solution that they came up with
is that God is both man and God. Okay,
it's really important for you guys to
appreciate.
Jesus has a dual nature. Both God and
man, both divine and both
um human. Why is this important? You
have to have Jesus both as divine and as
human. Why? Do you guys know why?
You can't be like this guy's a man. You
can't be this guy's a god. You have to
It has to be both. Why? Yes. Well, from
a literary perspective, like we all like
a main character we can relate to. And
if Jesus was holy God, then we can't
relate to him that much. And if he was
holy human, then well, what business
does he have doing all these nice things
for us?
>> Um, okay. But there's actually a much
more reason. Yes.
>> Um, because therefore he can save all
the human
>> by how?
>> By um salvation.
Um okay so the main reason is the
crucifixion right right doesn't make
sense guys
crucifixion so idea is that his
sacrifice only makes sense if he could
die you understand God you crucify him
who cares that's nothing so he needed to
have a human element in order for his
sacrifice to be worthwhile to be worthy
of redeeming us. Okay, so that's one
major theological debate and quite
honestly it still goes on today. There
are like literally hundreds and hundreds
different of different sects of
Christianity arguing about this. Okay.
Um but the big really big question is
the relationship between God, the Holy
Spirit and Jesus, right? Because now
we've um affirmed that Jesus is God.
That's why we worship him. That's why
we're Christians. But why are why does
the God appear in the Bible and why does
the Holy Spirit and why is Jesus? Right?
Worship between these three. And
historically there have been different
explanations.
The council is important because it
established the holy trinity.
Okay. The holy trinity. The concept here
is
God, Jesus, and the Holy Spirit are
separate but one. It doesn't make sense.
They are both different but the same at
the same time. Okay. So, the council
establishes the Holy Trinity. And quite
honestly, most Christians were a gasast
at this idea. This started civil wars.
This this is what launched civil wars
throughout the Christian world. Okay.
But the Bosian Empire enforced the Holy
Trinity throughout and even today
there's still arguments about the the
Holy Trinity. Okay. So this is a custom
really important idea to keep in mind
because finally we'll discuss this from
the divine harmony. Then we go to about
400. Why is this important? because Rome
falls. The barbarians, Visigoths, they
overrun Rome. And if you're a Christian,
you're like, "This is a question of
faith." Because you were taught that
Rome is heaven on earth. It's where the
Catholic Church is.
So why would God not protect
Rome? And so at this time um the major
Catholic theologian named Augustine okay
um he writes a book called city of God
in the city of God what it argues is
there are two cities in the world there
is Rome and there's Jerusalem Rome is a
seat of temporal power Jerusalem is a
seat called spiritual power.
Rome was meant to fall so that Jerusalem
may rise. What is Jerusalem? Jerusalem
is the Catholic Church. Okay? So in
other words, the Catholic Church is out
of history.
The Catholic Church does not care
who is king. The Catholic Church does
not care who is rich or who is poor.
Doesn't matter. is all temporal issues,
earthly issues. What the Catholic Church
cares about is who goes to heaven and
why. Okay. So, Augustine establishes
this separation between church and state
where the church is out of history,
beyond history. It doesn't care who's
king. This is why in the 1800
Charlemagne is a problem because
Charlemagne wants to have the authority
of Catholic Church because he wants to
become the new Roman Emperor and the
Pope grants it to him. The pope
anoints him emperor of the Holy Roman
Empire. Right? If you don't have holy in
here, holy, then you need the church. So
now the church becomes embedded in
temple politics. And this is what leads
to Dante running the Divine Comedy
because he is angry at the fact that
because the church has involved itself
in temporal politics, now all of Europe
is in factional politics. Right now you
have two major seats of power. The Holy
Roman Empire Empire as well as the
Catholic Church. And they're always
fighting. Okay? The Holy R woman Roman
Empire is fighting to figure out who
will be pope. That's not a temp temporal
issue. That's not a worldly issue. The
Vatican is fighting to install a
friendly emperor in the Holy Roman
Empire. Okay, this is happening for
centuries and this is leading to wars
throughout Europe. It's also leading to
massive oppression, massive censorship,
the destruction of creativity in Europe.
And this empowers Dante to write the
divine comedy to address a lot of these
histories. Okay. So what Dant is going
to do is the first thing he's going to
do is
present the official story of the
Catholic Church and then he's going to
make some adjustments to it. Okay. To
reconcile the differences. Now,
um, some really important history that
Dante will go into is
[clears throat]
why did Jesus have to die? Okay.
What was the point of the death of
Jesus? And as you know, it was to redeem
us from our original sin, right? Adam
and Eve at the beginning of time.
God gave him a very simple order, very
simple instruction. Do not eat that
stupid fruit. Okay? Anything else, but
don't eat that fruit. And they eat the
fruit. And that's the original sin. And
then we humans because we disobey God
became lost
uh became evil. And it was Jesus who
came to redeem us in the eyes of God.
Right?
And so
um
that's why he was crucified.
Now if you read the Bible, what it tells
you is that the Jews were responsible
for the death of Jesus. So now God has
to avenge his only son. So what happens
in the year 70?
the Romans destroy the second temple.
Okay? [clears throat] And if you know
modern day history, that's that's what's
led to a lot of problems today. Okay?
But in the year 70, the Jews rebelled
against the Romans. The Romans under
Titus sent a huge army and they burned
down the second temple. And this revenge
for
um uh for the Jews betraying Jesus.
And so if you're a Christian, you learn
this history.
But obviously this raises a lot of
issues.
Why did why was murder the murder of
Jesus necessary to redeem us, right?
What is one wrong
make right? Okay, that doesn't really
make any sense. Also,
why would God need to punish the Jews if
this all part of the plan to begin with,
right? The Jews did nothing wrong. Okay,
yes, the Jews did betray uh Jesus, but
wasn't this part of the plan to begin
with? The Jews were just doing their
part. So, why did God have to punish the
Jews? Okay. So clearly there are issues
with
um this history and this history is
important because if you know European
Europe your European history it's led to
a lot of evil in Europe right for
example anti-semitism in Europe. Um so
Dante feels compelled to reconcile this
history and present it in a way that um
we can appreciate and which will lead us
[clears throat] closer to the monad to
God. And that really is the genius of
Dante where he can take this complex
convoluted history and turn it into a
philosophy for us to appreciate and for
us to act upon. Okay, does that make
sense? Any questions about this
introduction before we read Dante? I
guess.
>> Um, so does Dante believe that Jesus is
God or not? Or does he like to how many
parts does he agree with the Catholic
Church?
Okay. Um, that's a really good question
and the answer is we'll never know
because
Dante is running at a time in history
where um, you could be killed for
defying the Catholic Church, for
committing heresy. Okay. So, a lot of
things he does, it's going to be subtle.
It's going to be nuance. We'll never
truly know his true feelings, but if I
[clears throat] had to guess,
um, I would say that
Dante in his interpretation of the Bible
in in his interpretation of Jesus, he
felt that Jesus was a great spiritual
leader who was divine in nature, but so
is Dante. Okay, does that make sense? So
um what what Donna would say is look I'm
writing this poetry because God has
taken possession of me in order to relay
a message to all humanity and that's
what he would probably say about Jesus
Jesus as well where Jesus is divinely
inspired to spread a message of hope and
salvation to the people around him.
Okay. Now um sorry did did you want to
say something? I wanted to say something
like the the the history you just
presented earlier about Jesus's murder,
so to speak. Was it meant to be factual
or was it meant to be biblical?
>> Um, so this is the official Catholic
history,
right? I'm I'm not I'm not making a
comment if this is true or false. I'm
just saying this is what the Catholic
Church teaches its followers.
>> Okay. Okay. Am I right here?
Okay. If if you're Catholic and I get it
wrong, please please let me know.
Okay, I present this to you because um
Justinian will say the same thing. Okay,
but I'm putting this in simple terms so
we we understand what what what he's
saying and then Donnie is going to argue
against this. All right. Okay. Uh so
let's go back to Jesus. [clears throat]
All right. So um
something to keep in mind about Jesus is
if you really want to understand the
essence of Jesus
there is a part of Bible that I think is
pure poetry it itself has to be divinely
inspired just like the divine comedy and
um I think we should read it together
okay it's called the sermon sermon on
the mount okay so so so Carol will read
the sermon on the mount Okay, just so we
can understand who Jesus is and how he
thinks.
We don't have to read all of it. It's
pretty long, but but we we'll read a few
paragraphs. Okay.
Um,
this is from the Gospel of Matthew, um,
the NIV version.
Blessed are the poor in spirit, for
theirs is the kingdom of heaven. Blessed
are those who mourn, for they will be
comforted. Blessed are the meek, for
they will inherit the earth. Blessed are
those who hunger and thirst for
righteousness, for they will be filled.
Blessed are the merciful, for they will
be shown mercy. Blessed are the pure in
heart, for they will see God. Blessed
are the peacemakers, for they will be
called children of God. Blessed are
those who are persecuted because of
righteousness, for theirs is the kingdom
of heaven.
>> Okay. All right. Stop. Okay. So, um, you
can hear the poetry. You can hear the
beauty and the truth. Now,
um this is very powerful. It I think it
moves every one of us today. Okay? Some
sometimes I just cry hearing this. But
this is especially powerful
2,000 years ago when Jesus was alive.
Why? Because the Roman eye Roman Empire
was really really evil. The Roman
Empire's
Romana marked a time of tremendous
inequality where few people had
everything and where most people were
slaves.
So in this time, what do you do? Well,
if you revolt like Spartacus, they'll
come and they'll crucify you and your
family, right? You you can try to rebel,
but there's no point because it is the
empire. It is everywhere. It is
everything.
you can't possibly get become rich
because all the wealth has been
monopolized. Yes,
>> I would have to say that uh while this
is from a modern day perspective true, I
think it is a slightly anacronistic
perspective because in the age of the
Romans, wealth equality was a thing that
was taken was taken like as granted in
society and also Christianity is not
free of its wealth inequality especially
after its legalization and also also
Roman slavery was not as widespread or
as cruel as we think many Roman
citizens. would enter slavery as a way
to free themselves from their debt. So
I'm saying that while this all of this
is true from a present day and from a
Christian perspective, it is slightly
anacronistic.
>> Okay. So let me ask you this question.
Let's just say that you are a young
person living in the world today. The
baby boomers have everything.
You went to school. Now you have
$100,000 in debt. Um and you have
absolutely no job prospects. The best
you can hope for is maybe to become a
gig worker, right? Work driving a yuber.
Uh you have no chance of getting
married.
You have
uh no prospect of ever owning a home.
How do you feel?
How would you feel? I'd be pretty
pissed.
>> Yeah. Again, I think this well this is
absolutely true on present day and it
highlights some of the most poant
questions that we face in our present
day. I think it's a slightly
anacronistic perspective if we apply it
to the Roman Empire.
>> Okay. All right. Fine. Okay. But I'm
just saying like maybe a thousand years
ago we'd be like, "Wow, young people in
the year 2026 have it all, man. They
have cars, they have computers, they
have air conditioning. They are. They
must be the happiest young people ever
in human history, right? You guys have
porn in your computer,
right? You guys can fly to Beijing and
take this class. What are you
complaining about?
Well, I'm pretty sure the slaves back in
the Roman times had a lot more to
complain about than you guys. Okay. All
right. So, even though Okay. Well, maybe
they weren't that bad off. Relatively,
they felt hopeless. Okay, if you were a
slave in the Roman period during this
time, and again, 90% of the population
were either poor or slaves, you hated
your life, right? And so, what is your
hope? Well, what Jesus is saying is
you have been brainwashed. You have been
indoctrinated to believe that only
wealth matters.
Okay? Blessed are the poor. You are
what? Who God truly truly loves.
Don't seek wealth. Seek poverty. Poverty
is the path to God. That it's a message
of hope. It's a message of salvation.
It's also a message of liberation.
The greatest revolution you can commit
as an individual
is to recognize the humanity, the
divinity in yourself regardless of what
people in authority tell you. Right?
This is why this message is so powerful
and it resonates and that's why
Christianity spread so far because it is
a message that speaks to the human heart
in a time of anguish. Okay? And this is
this is a spirit by the way that Dante
will try to remember or conjure up in
the divine comedy. Jesus was not an
empire builder. He didn't care about the
church. There's no Catholic church um
when he was around. He was part of a
movement called the poor. Okay? Have you
guys learned this history? The poor.
Okay.
the poor and the poor. This movement is
basically we give out material wealth.
We will travel as beggars and we will
only
u accept charity. Okay, we won't accept
money but we'll accept food and lodging.
And there's a very powerful passage in
was it Matthew? But like basically
actually it's it's in most of the
gospels, but a young man uh says to
Jesus, "I want to be like you. How can I
follow you?" And Jesus is like, "Do good
works." And then the young man's like,
"No, no, I want to do more." And Jesus
is Jesus says, "If you really want to be
one of God, give up your wealth." And
then the man says, "I can't do that
because I'm filthy rich, man. I have lot
of money. I'm not going to give up my
wealth. And then Jesus says to others,
"Truly, it is harder for a man to
what what was it?" Yeah. Right. Yeah.
Yeah. Go ahead.
>> It's harder for the camel to pass
through the eye of an needle than for a
rich man to get into heaven.
>> Exactly. Okay. That is Jesus. That is a
spirit of Jesus that Dante recognizes.
And um when Dante talks about uh St. uh
Francis of Aisi right he will conjure up
he will help us remember that this was
the real Jesus a man who taught people
the path to salvation
is through your spirituality. It is
through kindness [clears throat]
through generosity through love. Okay,
that is the Jesus that I think Dante
understood. Yes.
>> But wasn't Dante an aristocrat himself?
Like someone who had power and money and
stuff like
>> Hey, sorry. What What's your point here?
>> Well, I mean, if he wanted to be like
Jesus then or like or spread his
message, then
he didn't live exactly that life. He
lived a life of
>> like power, right? Or like he was an
aristocrat himself. Um so um first of
all I mean Dante came from a good family
but he was not an aristocrat by the
standards of Flor Florence. Okay. Also
let me ask you this question. Was St.
Francis of Aisi you know the man who
became the founder of the physical
movement who gave up all wealth. Was he
born rich or poor? Do you know? Guess
he was very very rich. his family was
very very rich. And that's why what he
did was so significant. Right? If you're
born poor and you're like, I don't want
money. Is that hard? But if you're born
rich, you're like, you know what? All my
friends are rich. I' I've born rich, but
I'm going to give up all this money.
That is an action that is truly
inspired, right? It's truly divine.
Yes.
>> Um, this isn't related to Jesus
necessarily. So what Dante what I think
Dante is doing I think it's actually a
pioneering it's actually a early version
of Protestantism. So a a kind of place
where you return to God where you return
to Jesus instead of returning to the
Catholic Church. So my personal opinion
about the Catholic Church is that
despite preaching the gospel of poverty,
despite condemning having a lot of money
and using it to do evil things, it
actually enabled a lot of the power
structures that allowed medieval
European society to become so unequal
and so feudal. So my point is that Dante
is actually subtly pioneering this
return to Jesus's own values, bypassing
the Catholic Church.
>> Yes. Okay. All right. So that's true.
But um something that you guys don't
appreciate is there was always
opposition towards the Catholic Church
throughout history. Do you understand?
The Protestant movement was not new. It
was always there. Okay. So there were
two um major oppositions to the church.
Okay. The first argument is that the
church is too worldly.
Meaning that these priates were these
bishops were filthy filthy rich. And
like sorry, but the apostles, you know,
they swore to poverty. Jesus swore to
poverty. So that's betraying the church.
So throughout this history, okay, it's
been covered up, but throughout this
history, there were all these movements
throughout Europe that um criticized the
church for corruption and who sought to
return to a life of poverty. Some of
these movements the church actually
co-opted, right? So the um the
Benedictines and the Dominicans and the
Franciscans were co-opted by the church
but they came about because of their
harsh criticis criticism of church power
and wealth. Okay. The second thing about
the church was
um
for Jesus taught. Okay, this is really
important. You read the Bible, he
actually says this. But Jesus taught
that we all have a direct connection to
God. Okay? That's what Jesus taught. But
the church says, "No, no, we are born in
sin. Therefore, we have betrayed God.
Therefore, we must now rely on the
church to connect us back to God."
Okay? But throughout most of this
most of this time, there were a lot of
people who refused to accept this. And
the one major groups of course is called
the Cathars. I'm not sure if you know
this history, the Cathars.
Okay, there are a lot of these um
Christian sects that taught that we had
a direct connection to God. Okay. Um and
so they were suppressed. This launched
the Albin the Albaian crusade.
Okay. So this is really important for
you guys to understand. The Protestant
movement was not a sudden revolution. It
was always there. The Protestant
revolution was just successful. Okay.
But there but throughout history at no
point was there not opposition towards
Catholic Church for these two reasons.
Because the church was seen as corrupt
and because the church denied direct
access to God.
Okay. And this is something that Dante
will discuss at great depth in the div
in the divine comedy. Does it make
sense?
So one last thing that you guys need to
know is in the year 1321, this this is
the year when Dante finished the line
comedy and the moment he finished like I
don't know a few months later he died.
Okay. So basically you could argue that
he kept him he kept himself alive in
order to finish the line comedy and then
when he finished it he's like my mission
is done. I can now rest and be with with
God. But in the year 1321
um at this time in history
the explanation for why Jesus had to die
on the cross is radically different from
today. today. Why? Why do we think Jesus
died on the cross? What what's what's
explanation
to redeem us from our sins? Right? Okay.
Back then, the most popular explanation
is something called the ransom theory.
The ransom theory.
Okay. And it goes like this.
What? Who made us eat that fruit? Satan,
right? Disguised as a serpent.
So when we ate that fruit, we turned
away from God and became slaves to
Satan.
So now this is a problem because if God
is to redeem us, he needs to pay a
ransom to Satan, right?
Let me finish first. Okay? And so if
you're God and you need to make a deal
with Satan, what can you offer to Satan
that would allow him to free us? The
answer is his only son. Okay.
But Satan
didn't recognize that
the only son was so divine that he could
resurrect. Okay. So Satan So even though
Jesus did go to hell, he was able to
escape it as well. So at this time in
history, this is the most popular
explanation for why Jesus had to die on
the cross as a ransom for our sins.
Okay? And over time it becomes
generalized to become he redeemed us
from our sins. So this is the most
popular theory at this time and Dante
will respond to this theory. Uh yes.
>> So I think uh again I'm just picking out
words picking hairs here but I'm saying
that Satan made us eat the fruit. Satan
did not make us do anything. Satan
tempted us to eat the fruit and we did
it of our own free will. Because if
Satan made us ate the fruit and if we
really became slaves to him, then Satan
will be more powerful than God because
he could sub subvert God's most most
holy most precious gift which is our
free will, which doesn't make any sense,
>> right? Yeah. Okay. Yeah, that that
that's right. So we we are our free will
chose to become slaves to Satan. Does
that make sense? Because when we became
tempted by Satan, we turned away from
God and became like Satan.
Okay?
>> But that is assuming that Satan is as
powerful as God and Satan has the right
to receive the gift of reward.
>> Okay? So, so look, I'm not arguing about
theology, okay? I'm not arguing about
these ideas. I'm just saying what people
believe at this time and what the church
taught at this time. And because I need
I need to explain to you why Ton Dant is
doing what he's doing. Okay. Okay. I'm
not going to argue this is right or
wrong. I'm just saying this is what
people believed at this time. Uh does
that make sense, guys? Okay. All right.
So, this is the background. And so,
we're not going to read uh Dante
together. Okay. And so, for the first
KTO, Justin is just going to tell us the
history of the Catholic Church beginning
with Rome. And keep in mind there are
two things that upset Dante. The first
is why did Jesus have to die? The second
is why did um um
uh uh God have to destroy the temple?
Okay. All right. Uh can you read Carol
please?
Paradise KTO 6 from the from the
beginning after Constantine had turned
the eagle counter to heaven's course the
course it took behind the ancient one
who wed Levvenia.
>> Okay. So Constantine of course is a
person who makes Christianity the
official religion
of Rome. The eagle is the Roman Empire
itself. Okay. The eagle is a standard of
the Roman Empire. When you see the word
eagle it means the Roman Empire. Uh the
ancient one who led Levvenia is Inius.
Okay. Um,
and in many ways, Divine Comedy, it is a
reimagination of Virgil's great epic
poem, The Ini. I'll discuss this next
week. Okay. But but that that's some
background. Keep on going.
>> 100 years and more, the bird of God
remained near Europe's borders, close to
the peaks from which it first emerged.
Beneath the shadow of the sacred wings,
it ruled the world from hand to hand
until that governing changing became my
task. Caesar I was and am Justinian who
through the will of primal love I feel
removed the vain and needless from the
laws. But I grew before I grew attentive
to this labor, I held that but one
nature and no more was Christ. And in
that faith I was content. But then the
blessed Agapitus, he who was chief
shepherd with his words turned me to
that faith which has truth and purity. I
did believe him and now clearly see his
faith as you with contradic.
As soon as my steps shared the church's
path, God of his grace inspired my high
task as pleased him. I was fully drawn
to that and trusting to my belliserius
my arms I found a sign for me to rest
from war. Heaven's right hand so favored
him.
>> Okay. All right. So so the background is
this. Okay. Justinian is emperor of the
Basian Empire the eastern Roman Empire.
And at this point in history uh the
Roman Empire is divided into the eastern
half and the western half. Okay. It's
basically split in two. And because it's
split in two, there are many different
variants of Christianity. Most variants
do not accept the Holy Trinity. Okay?
So, Justinian goes on this holy crusade
to conquer and unite all the Roman
Empire and enforce the Holy Trinity on
everyone and he succeeds. And his
general at this time was Bis Biserius.
Okay, keep on going.
My answer to the question you first
asked ends here. And yet the nature of
this answer leads me to add a sequel so
that you may see with how much reason
they attack the sacred standard. Those
who seem to act on its behalf and those
opposing it. See what great virtue made
that eagle worthy of reverence beginning
from that hour when palace died that it
might gain a kingdom. You know that for
300 years and more it lived in Alba
until at the end three still fought
three still fought three contending for
that standard. You know how under seven
kings it conquered a neighbors its
neighbors in the year reaching from
wrong Sabine women to Lricius's
grief.
>> Okay so the woman Lricia's uh suicide
this is all part of the early history of
the Roman Republic. Okay, we don't have
time to go into this history, but what
he's doing is summarizing the history of
the Roman Republic, which then gives
birth to the Roman Empire. Okay, keep on
going.
and what it did when carried by
courageous Romans who hurried to
encounter Brenis Purus and other
principates and cities through this for
quitus qui Quincius who named for his
disheveled hair. The Di Desai and Febi
gained the fame I gladly honor. That
standard brought the pride of Arabs low
when they had followed Hannibal across
those alpine rocks from which po you
descend. Beneath that standard, Shipio
Pompei, though young, triumphed and to
that hill beneath which you were born,
that standard seemed most harsh. Then,
near the time when heaven wished to
bring all of the world to heaven's way,
Serene Caesar, as Rome had willed, took
up that standard.
And what it did from var to rine was
seen by the Iser sa zon and sen and all
the valley floors whose rivers feed the
rone. And what it did once it had left
Ravena and left the Rubicon was such a
flight as neither tongue nor writing can
describe. That Standard led the legions
onto Spain, then toward Durazzo, and it
struck Felia so hard that the warm Nile
could feel that hurt. It saw again its
source and Tandros and Sim Samoas and
the place where Hector lies. Then roused
itself the worst for Poleamy.
from Egypt lightning like it fell on
Juba and then it hurried to the west of
you where it could hear the trumpet of
Pompei.
>> Okay, so again he's just reciting or
just summarizing Roman history where and
but the point is the tone is that this
is all pre-ordained by God. The rise of
Rome was so quick that it had to be
divine. Then with Rome comes Julius
Caesar who will now birth the Roman
Empire by conquering Gaul by conquering
everyone basically. And it's all been
pre-ordained. Okay? Nothing can stop it.
Not not the Carthaginians
uh not even civil war can stop God's
plan. Keep on going
because of what that standard did. With
him who bore it next, Brutus and Cashes
howl in hell, and grief seized Modina
Perugia. Because of it, sad Cleopatra
weep still as she fled that standard.
From the aspen
and atrocious death, and with that very
bearer, it then reached the Red Sea
shore. With him, that emblem brought the
world such peace that Janice's shrine
was shut. But what the standard that has
made me speak had done before or then
was yet to do throughout the mortal
realm where it holds rule comes to seem
faint and and and insignificant if one
with clear sight and pure sentiment sees
what it did in the third Caesar's hand.
>> Okay. So the third Caesar is Tiberious
Caesar, right? The first is Julius
Caesar, Augustus Caesar and the third is
Tiberious Caesar. Tiberius Caesar is
important because that this is during
the time of Jesus, right? Jesus is now
working as a prophet during this time.
Keep on going
>> for the true justice that inspires me,
granted to it in that next Caesar's
hand, the glory of avenging his own
wrath. Now, marvel here at what I show
to you.
>> Sorry. The glory of avenging his own
wrath refers to
the crucifixion of Jesus, right?
God is angry at us. In order to
dissipate his anger, he must sacrifice
his only son, Jesus. Okay, that this is
what it refers to. Keep on going.
>> Now, marvel here at what I showed to you
with Titus. Afterward, it hurried toward
avenging vengeance for the ancient sin.
>> So, Titus is the general that will
destroy the Jewish rebellion and burn
down the second temple. Okay? This is
and and the Catholic Church teaches
people at this time that this is
vengeance for the Jews betrayal of
Jesus. Keep on going.
>> And when the Lombard tooth bit Holy
Church, then Charlemagne under the
eagle's wings through victories he
gained brought help to her. Now you can
judge those I condemned above and judge
how much men have offended have become
the origin of all your evils. For some
oppose the universal emblem with yellow
liies. Others claim that emblem for
party. It is hard to see who is worse.
Let jibalines pursue their undertakings
beneath another sign. For those who
sever this sign and justice are bad
followers.
>> Okay. So now what Justin is saying is
that in this time people have misused
the legacy of the Roman Empire to
conduct their own wars for political
gain. Okay. So I said before that with
the birth of the Holy Roman Empire the
church becomes embroiled in European
geopolitics and this leads to wars
throughout this period. Dante is forced
into these wars because right now in
this in history this this about the year
1300 the Giblines and the Gves are at
war with each other. The Gves um support
the Pope the Giblines support the Holy
Roman Empire or the other way around. I
can't remember it. Okay. And what
happens is the Gs and Donny's part of
the G. They defeat the Giblines. And so
the the gelves control Florence. And
what happens next of course is you guys
know
the GS divide into two factions, the
blacks and the whites.
And these are before the same political
party. And now they're fighting each
other for power. And at first the whites
win and exile the black welves. The
black welves then stage a stage a combat
and then kick out the white which exiles
Dante. Okay. And what uh and what Donn
is saying to Justinian is that this is
all a corruption of the teachings of the
church. Okay. The church should not be
involved in temporal politics. We should
not be fighting uh for the legacy of
Rome. Okay. Keep on going.
>> And let not this new Charles strike at
it with his gels, but let him fear the
claws that stripped a more courageous
lion of its hide. The sons have often
wept for a father's fault. And let the
son not think that God will change the
emblem of his force for charles's liies.
This little planet is adorned with
spirits whose acts were righteous, but
who acted for the honor and the fame
that they would gain. And when desires
tend toward earthly ends, then so
deflected rays of the true love mount
toward the life above with lesser force.
Okay. So again this is a central idea in
divine comedy. Okay. God is always
calling to us. We always return want to
return to God. But because of free will
we can choose
where to direct our energies. If we
direct our energies towards God we
become closer to God. But if we direct
our energy towards power,
earthly gain, materialism then God then
we will turn away from God and God will
shine will shine less brightly on us.
Okay. Keep on going.
But part of our delight is measuring
rewards against our merit. And we see
that our rewards are neither less nor
more. Thus does the living justice make
so sweet the sentiments in us that we
are free of any turning toward iniquity.
Differing voices join to sound sweet
music. So do the different orders in our
life render sweet harmony among these
fears. And in this very pearl there also
shines the light of Romeo, of one whose
acts, though great and noble, met
ungratefulness.
And yet those provinileals who schemed
against him had little chance to laugh.
For he who finds harm to himself and
others's righteous acts takes the wrong
path. Of Raymond Behringer's four
daughters each became a queen. And this
poor and a stranger Romeo accomplished.
Then Behringer was moved by vicious
tongues to ask this just man for
accounting. One who given 10 gave Raymon
five and seven. And Romeo the poor the
old departed. And were the world to know
the heart he had while begging crust by
crust for his life bread. It though it
praise him now would praise him more.
>> Okay. So this is very similar to the
message of Jesus. Okay. Okay. What Jesus
taught his followers is all this wealth
that we see in this world, it's a false
wealth. It's nothing. It's poverty. The
true wealth is with God. So do what is
right and you'll be rewarded in heaven.
And that's what he's saying what what um
Don is saying for Justinian. There was a
man Romeo who was very much like Dante
who was participating in these wars but
because he chose to do good um the
people turned against him and even
though he suffered in on earth he was
exiled he was impoverished just like
Dante ultimately he was given uh
tremendous reward in heaven. Okay. So,
make your choice. You can either choose
a life of wealth here and a life of
poverty up there or a life of poverty
down here and a life of poverty up
there. Okay. It's entirely your choice.
It's your free will. Okay. All right.
So, what's happened is that we now know
the official story of the Catholic
Church as told by Justinian.
But again, this raises a question for
Dante, which is tell me exactly why
Jesus had to kill himself again.
It doesn't make any sense. Okay. And
what Beatus is going to do is explain
um Jesus sacrifice in a way that I think
is the most powerful explanation ever.
Okay. But before we start, does anyone
here
know why Jesus Jesus had to kill
himself?
>> Oh,
first. Yeah. Yeah. You go first.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Oh, yeah. I think Jesus is trying
to cure cure himself just because he
want to show that he's not he's really
the the the son of God because some
people keep doubt on him and even the
you the Judah you know the the the
disciple right who just said that he
just you know because of the silver coin
right he just tried to betray the the
Jesus maybe Jesus want to people to know
that he is the true God
>> yeah and certain certain denominations
teach this yes to prove that he is truly
divine because he can resurrect himself
Okay.
>> The [clears throat] sacrificing your own
son has to be like the biggest
representation of love and that's the
love that God has towards us.
>> Okay. Could you elaborate on that?
>> As in there's there's nothing harder
that someone could do than sacrifice
their own son. But the fact that God did
it for us to clean us from our sins
shows how much he loves us.
Um, okay.
But
did he really sacrifice his son?
Because Jesus didn't die, right?
>> But he was willing to show us.
>> Okay. He showed us. Okay. Yes. Okay.
That that's actually Donna's explanation
as well. Yes.
>> I have like two questions. The first one
is that uh Jesus sacrificed to prove
that he is divine. So if he proves that
he is divine through a concrete thing
like rising up from the dead, then
that's not that's not faith anymore, is
it? That's just I saw him rise from the
dead. It's a fact. And the second
question is that God sacrificed his son.
So uh as God's son, Jesus is both human
and divine. And because he's he is part
human, he has free will and therefore he
can choose whether or not to be
sacrificed. So I think maybe a more
appropriate framing would be Jesus chose
to sacrifice himself. God did not
sacrifice anybody because God cannot
take away that gift.
>> Right. No, you're exactly right that No,
no, you're right. Jesus did sacrifice
himself. It was his choice to sacrifice
him. You're right. Okay. But the idea is
that Jesus and God are the same thing.
Right. Okay. All right. So So let let
let's read this. Okay. And this is a
really powerful section. I want to make
sure we appreciate
the logic here. Okay, we we we can skip
the first three lines because that's
just Latin. Okay.
Thus, even as he wheeled to his own
music, I saw that substance sing, that
spirit flame above whom double lights
were twined. and he and his companions
moved within their dance. And as if they
were swift as sparks, they sped out of
my sight because of sudden distance. I
was perplexed, and to myself, I said,
"Tell her, tell her, tell her the lady
who can slake my thirst with her sweet
drops." And yet the reverence that
possesses all of me, even on hearing
only be and ice, had bowed my head. I
seemed a man asleep. But Beatrice soon
ended that for she began to smile at me
so brightly that even in fire a man
would still feel glad according to my
nevering judgment. The question that
perplexes you is how just vengeance can
deserve just punishment.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. This is a really
important sentence. Okay. What it means
is God should be angry at us for
betraying him, for
eating the food when he told us not to.
Okay, this is just vengeance. He should
be angry at us.
But
why would it involve the sacrifice of
his only son, right? Just punishment.
Why should this man who's innocent,
Jesus, have to sacrifice himself in
order to appease God's anger at us? That
doesn't make any sense, right? Okay. Uh,
keep on going.
But I shall quickly free your mind from
doubt and listen carefully. The words I
speak will bring the gift of a great
truth in reach. Since he could not
endure the helpful curb on his
willpower, the man who was not born
damning himself damned all his progeny.
>> Okay, stop. Who is this man?
>> Yeah, it's Adam, obviously. Come on.
Right. Okay, keep on going.
For this mankind lay sick in the abyss
of a great error for long centuries
until the word of God willed to descend
to where the nature that was sundered
from its maker was united to his person
by the sole act of his eternal love.
>> Okay. So now there's a separation
between God and us.
And the question is how do you
reconcile? Right? There's anger now. God
is angry at us and we um basically
screwed up and we don't even know how to
ask for forgiveness. Okay, so this is a
shism. This is a separation. Okay, keep
on going.
Now set your sight on what derives from
that. This nature thus united to its
maker was good and pure even as when
created. But in itself, this nature had
been banished from paradise because it
turned aside from its own path, from
truth, from its own life.
>> Okay? So, we were born good. Okay? And
we know we're born good because in the
Bible, it says that when God created
man, God breath breathed
the spark of life into us. Okay? So,
there's an essence of God within us.
Therefore, we are born good. But because
of free will, we can choose to do stupid
things. We can choose a path of evil.
Once you pick a path of evil, what often
happens is that becomes like a snow
snowball, okay? Rolling down and
accumulating. So we do one stupid act,
then we do another, then we do more
evil, keeps on going. And we don't
really know how to get back on the
correct path. Okay. Uh, keep on going.
Carol,
>> line 40. Thus, if the penalty the cross
inflicted is measured by the nature he
assumed, no one has ever been so justly
stung. Yet none was ever done so great a
wrong if we regard the person made to
suffer he who had gathered in himself
that nature.
Thus from one action issued differing
things. God and the Jews were pleased by
one same death. Earth trembled for that
death and heaven opened. You need no
longer find it difficult to understand
when it is said that just vengeance was
then avenged by a just court. But I now
see your understanding tangled by
thought on thought into a knot from
which with much desire your mind awaits
release. You say what I have heard is
clear to me but this is hidden from me.
Why God w precisely this pathway for our
redemption.
>> Okay. Right. Okay. So this is the
question. Okay. If you are God and you
are infinite and eternal, why do you
have to pick a particular way in which
an innocent man, Jesus, was punished? He
could choose to be punished, but
it seems unjust. Okay, it seems wrong.
Okay, keep on going.
Verse
58, brother, this ordinance is buried
from the eyes of everyone whose
intellect has not matured within the
flame of love.
>> Okay, so what what's she saying here?
This is really important, is you don't
understand because you don't love
enough. If you become a parent and you
love your child unconditionally,
then you understand why God had to do
what he did. Okay?
God is eternal and infinite. There are a
million solutions and he picked the best
possible solution. And if it sounds
stupid to us, if it sounds wrong to us,
it's not his problem. It's our problem.
It's because we don't understand love
enough. Keep on going.
Verse 61. Nevertheless, since there is
much attempting to find this point, but
little understanding, I shall tell why
that way was the most fitting. The godly
goodness that has banished every envy
from its own self, burns itself, and
sparkling so it shows eternal beauties.
All that deres directly from this
goodness is everlasting, since the seal
of goodness impresses an imprint that
never alters. Whatever reigns from it
immediately is fully free, for it is not
constrained by any influence of other
things. Even as it conforms to that
goodness, so does it please it more. The
sacred order that gleams in all things
is most bright within those things most
like itself. The human being has all
these gifts, but if it loses one, then
its nobility has been undone.
Only man's sin anuls man's liberty makes
him unlike the highest good so that in
him the brightness of its light is
dimmed. Let me
>> stop. Okay. All right. Okay. So, do you
guys understand what he's saying? What
Petri is saying is that God is perfect.
God is pure love. God is all generosity,
all forgiveness, all truth. And we were
created in his image. And so we share
all his qualities. The problem is we
have free will and we are immature. And
the moment we choose to sin, we turn
away from God and therefore we lose our
divinity. And once we pick this path, we
can only compound our own mistakes, our
own evil. Okay, does that make sense?
The moment we turn away from God by
sinning, we're lost now. Okay, keep on
going. Verse
82.
And man cannot regain it his dignity
unless where sin left emptiness, man
fills that void with just amends for
evil pleasure. For for when your nature
sinned so totally within its seed, then
from these dignities, just as from
paradise, that nature parted, and they
could never be regained, if you consider
carefully by any way that did not pass
across one of these fords, either
through nothing other than his mercy,
God had to pardon man, or of himself,
man had to profer payment for his folly.
Okay. All right. So, okay. What she's
saying here is, okay, we screwed up and
this is the worst thing that we could
have done. Okay. And now there only two
ways to redemption. The first way is if
we make amends.
Okay.
But there's a problem with that. What's
the problem with that?
How can we make amends for the original
sin?
Okay, first of all, what is the original
sin? Do do you guys know what the
original sin is?
>> Uh uh yeah, go ahead first and and then
you Okay,
>> we ate from the knowledge.
>> But but what is that? What motivated us?
>> Uh yes. And and and then you like like I
know you know. Okay. But but yeah, go
ahead.
So basically like uh there was the
garden of Eden and there was Satan. He
turned into a snake and he was like,
"Hey Eve, eat this apple." And Eve,
>> it wasn't an apple, by the way. But but
but why do we do it? Why do we eat the
fruit?
>> Because we Well, the problem that God
has with it is that we disobeyed him. He
told us don't eat the fruit and we ate
the fruit.
>> Why was he angry at disobedience?
>> Um
sorry go ahead. The fact that we want to
become God.
>> Exactly. Do you understand? The problem
was not disobedience. The problem was a
serpent told Eve. You eat this food and
you'll become like God.
Meaning we want to overthrow God. Okay?
This is the original sin, not the stupid
fruit. Okay? Who cares if you eat the
fruit? The the original sin is our
hearts became evil. Our hearts became so
evil and vicious that we wanted to kill
God and become God ourselves. That is
the issue. Yes.
>> So where did it say that we want to kill
God? Like this is this is monotheism. I
know but like where do you say we want
to kill God? We want to be equal with
God. That does not mean we have to kill
him.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Sorry. Just just like
she said the saying you don't want to
kill him just you can't replace them.
You can be be like that but not
>> guys. Guys um you need to understand
something. Um when we we are working in
historical context do you understand at
this time in history what the Catholic
Church teaches its followers it's flock
is that the original sin is our pride
okay this is this historical fact
this started with the Bible and in the
Bible it literally says that the serpent
tempted Eve to eat the fruit because
it would make her like God. It's
literally in the Bible in Genesis. Okay.
Then what Augustine
who will take this and say the original
sin is our pride and this becomes the
official doctrine of the church. Okay,
you guys you guys appreciate this. I'm
not arguing with you this is right or
wrong. I'm saying this is what is
historically true and this is what
Beatric is saying. Okay, according to
the doctrine of the church, we want to
be like God and like how can you make
amends for that? And the answer is you
cannot make amends for that. You want to
kill God. Okay? There's no way that you
there's nothing that you could do to
appease God or make amends or redeem
yourself because you did the worst thing
possible in the universe. Okay?
Excuse me.
The worst thing that you could do. Yes.
Okay. But the worst thing that humanity
has ever done in the universe is to try
to kill God. Okay. Okay.
Verse 94.
Now fix your eyes on the profanity of
the eternal council. Heed as closely as
you are able to my reasoning. man in his
limits could not recompense. For no
obedience, no humility he offered later
could have been so deep that it could
match the heights he meant to reach
through disobedience.
Man lacked the power to offer
satisfaction by himself. Thus, there was
need for God through his own ways to
bring man back to life intact. I mean by
one way or by both. But since a deed
pleases its doer more, the more it shows
the goodness of the heart from which it
springs, the godly goodness that
imprints the world was happy to proceed
through both its ways to raise you up
again. Nor has there been, nor will
there be between the final night and the
first day a chain of re a chain of
action so lofty and so magnificent as he
enacted when he followed his two ways.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. So this is
beautiful. Okay. But this is the logic.
The logic is we can't forgive ourselves.
So God must redeem us. But God has to
redeem us in a way that changes us for
the better. And so he has his son. The
thing about his son is that it's a dual
nature, right? Both man and God. Okay?
So the fact that a man Jesus is going to
redeem us will give will will help save
us. Okay? Because now we are engaged in
our own salvation through Jesus. Does
that make sense guys? Keep on going.
Verse 115.
For God showed greater generosity in
giving his own self than that man might
be able to rise than if he simply
pardoned. for every other means fell
short of justice except the way whereby
the son of God humbled himself when he
became incarnate.
>> Okay, so there's a million solutions.
Okay, and God spent a thousand years,
2,000 years, who knows, thinking think
of a solution. And his answer is, well,
first of all, I can't just forgive these
guys. They learn nothing.
Um, and I need them to do it themselves,
but they're humans and they're kind of
lame, so they can't do it themselves.
So, the only solution is for the son of
God to become man. Okay, that's the only
solution. A million possible scenarios,
there's only one scenario that could
possibly redeem us, and it's for the son
of God to become man and to be
sacrificed. Okay, that's the only way
forward. Come on.
>> Verse 12, 12:1. Now to give all your
wishes full content, I go back to
explain one point so [clears throat]
that you too may see it plainly as I do.
You say, I see that water, see that fire
and air and earth and all that they
compose come to corruption and endure so
briefly.
>> All right. Stop. Okay. All right. So
what I'm going to do now is help us
appreciate
the genius of the sacrifice of Jesus.
Okay? So I'm going to give you a thought
experiment. The thought experiment is
this.
You are a mother or a father, who cares?
You're a parent. Okay? And you have a
daughter named Eve.
And one day you bring home a dog. Okay.
And
um Eve asks you,
"Do you love this dog more or do you
love me more?"
And we're like,
"We love you both. Come on, man. Of
course we love you both." And then Eve's
like, "Okay." Then Eve can't sleep
because she's really disturbed by this
question. Does my mother or father love
me more or love the dog more? Okay, so
she so then she comes up with this
brilliant solution to solve this problem
which is she kills the dog,
right? She's like, I'm going to kill the
dog and that's going to show me if my
parents love me more or love the dog
more. Okay.
Now,
as the parent,
you're completely screwed. Okay?
Because let's think about this.
What do you do?
You told Eve, you love them both. You
love both the dog and Eve, your
daughter. Your daughter is confused by
this. And so he's like, "Well, I'm
curious now who my parents really love,
so I'm gonna kill the dog and see what
happens." Okay.
And so what do you do?
Maybe I would just say that this dog is
the dog I love most and you're the
daughter I love most. So if in that case
>> the dog's dead.
>> Yeah. If in that case the the girl do
not like to test it because she knows
that he's the only uh one.
>> So the dog is dead. He's already dead.
>> Yeah. So, what do you do?
>> What do you do?
>> I would
um I mean in the context of Jesus, you
punish yourself in a way. So, they would
see that um what you did hurt them more.
Um and so
to you like to forgive them, you have to
punish yourself.
>> Yeah. Okay. Okay. So, that's the logic.
Okay. All right. So, like because you're
you're kind of screwed. Okay. If you
don't do anything, what's Eve going to
do next?
Kill more animals. Okay. So, you cannot
do any you cannot do nothing. You got to
be like, I forgive you, Eve. Oh, you're
just a kid. Don't worry about it. Okay.
You have to do something. Okay. But if
you punish her, that proves to her you
love the dog more.
>> Right? So, anything you do, you're kind
of screwed. So, your only solution,
okay, of a million possibilities is you
punish yourself. You hit yourself
to show Eve, I have to punish you, but
um and you punish yourself. And when she
sees that,
what does she think? She thinks my
father, my mother truly truly loves me.
And will she ever kill an animal again?
No. Okay. Because she's seen what will
happen if an animal dies, the parents
will suffer. And so she's convinced by
the love of the parent and therefore
she's now fully committed to loving her
parents to the best of the ability.
Okay, that's the logic behind the
sacrifice of Jesus to show all of us
that God truly loves us so that we can
now return to loving God. This is
reconciliation. Okay, does it make sense
guys? Uh yes. Um, I think this is a very
strange metaphor because if I was the
parent, I would send Eve to therapy.
Like I think you would send what?
>> I would send Eve to therapy. Like I
think this is a very absolute situation.
Like it's either punishment or it's
allowance. Like why couldn't there be a
middle? Why couldn't there be education
in the middle?
>> Okay. You send Eve to therapy.
Okay. What does a therapist tell Eve?
I'm I'm not I'm not a I'm not a
therapist, but therapy has been proven
to work on a lot a range of conditions
inre including sociopathy.
>> Okay. But like I but like like we're
just doing this as a thought expert.
Okay. All right. You know what? I'm
gonna call the police and the police
going to come and arrest Eve. Oh, you
know what? Screw this. I'm going to call
the therapist and the therapist will
come and solve this problem with me.
Is it will this make the things worse or
better?
>> Why?
>> Well, the the therapist would probably
side with Eve and then they would like
start to like call the dad a bad parent
or something.
>> No, no, no. What's the therapist going
to do? Have you guys been to a
therapist? Therapists don't do that.
>> They're going to interrogate Eve and
that's probably going to make her very
uncomfortable.
They'll probably a therapist will
probably make her take pills. Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. And that's a punishment in which
case what what what does it tell Eve
about her parents?
>> Her parents don't love her, man.
>> Right. They're like, I don't do this
crap. I'm going to send her to a
therapist. Yeah. No, I think that's uh
to be honest, I think in the context of
this metaphor, that is a really uh
irresponsible way of thinking because as
a parent, I am not a psychological
expert and I do not have the resources
to help my child and to help my child. I
have to give her I have to give my money
and give my time to someone who is more
licensed, who is more qualified than I
am to help my child.
>> Your your what?
But your parents know you the best. Like
your parents should be the ones that
could help you. you know, the random
stranger like I mean
>> doesn't work here in China, bro.
>> I don't I don't think this is really I
don't think this is really relevant. I
think that's the rational course of
action.
>> Yeah, but the point is not about what's
rational to do. It's about like Eve is
trapped in this dilemma where she
believes that if you send me to therapy,
if you punish me by just a little bit in
any means anyway, it shows to me that
you don't love me. Yeah, that's her
logic, you know. Then you you kind of in
her logic, you have, you know,
>> but how is therapy a punishment for her?
It is a punishment. Whether you slap
her, you scold her, you guarantee that
if you kill a dog,
>> okay, and you go to therapy, they're
going to make you take pills.
>> I guarantee you,
>> okay, and that may not be the best
solution.
>> Yes. But as a parent, do we take ease
logic as as permanent? Do we do we
accept that or do we do do we need to
kind of, you know, do something on our
own behalf to kind of try to tweak that
logic or change that logic?
>> I'm actually confused like how there
must be something wrong with Eve
beforehand like your education, right?
for for her to be able to kill the dog.
This is just
>> again we need to use our imagination,
>> right?
>> But I do look I do have kids. So it's
which is why this is particularly
concerning for me like I would be the
first guy to try to try to sit down with
Eve and try to understand where she
comes from and then and then we go from
there. like maybe maybe
you know
>> listen I listen um I have three kids and
any of them could pull this crap on on
us. I mean like that's just how kids
are.
I mean like I'm not saying my kids are
going to do this but I'm saying like I
can imagine them doing this thing doing
this crap on me. Yeah.
>> So um I noticed that a lot of you have
like issues with outsourcing help for
your kids. Well, what I have to say is
uh your kid needs food and your kids
needs water, right? So, as a parent, are
you going to farm the food yourself and
get the water from the river yourself
because you want to do everything for
your kid because you're the one who
knows them best? Of course not.
>> But I I don't understand why you're
convinced that a therapist knows exactly
what he or she is doing. I
>> you're you're convinced that a stranger
with a PhD
knows more about the child than you, the
parent.
>> Um, yes. I'm convinced that they know
more than you. I'm not saying that they
know everything. I'm convinced that they
know more about the child's behavior,
behavioral patterns than you do.
>> Okay. But then there's a question of
risk, right? Like the therapist has
different skin in the game than you as
the parent. So naturally even though the
therapist might might have the set of
tools the application of those tools
coupled with the risks you take as the
parent to the kid I think in the end the
parent it still falls on the parent.
>> Okay. Are you okay are you okay with
this scenario? Okay. Let's just say
God's like you know what I really
shouldn't send my son to crucify
himself. That's kind of stupid. I I
don't know what I'll do. I'll create
this alien species. Okay that is
infinitely wise. I'll have them calm and
rule over humanity.
Are you okay with that?
>> It depends on what way they're winning
over you. The thing about therapy that
most people don't realize is that the
therapist doesn't force you to believe
anything. The therapist doesn't yell at
you. The therapist ask you and they
subtly guide you towards something
better. They give you a choice. They
give you your free will. They respect
your free will. That's what a lot of
people don't realize.
>> Okay. So, you and I are just have to
disagree about therapists. Okay. All
right. therapists don't actually well it
doesn't matter. Okay. All right. Okay.
But but but we're trying to explain the
logic of Dante, right? And this is a
really good explanation and I think it's
a very convincing explanation for why
Jesus had to die. Okay? It is not about
redemption. It's not about justice or
vengeance. It's really about inspiration
and education. Right? Because once we've
seen and once we know
that Jesus killed himself for our sins,
it gives us a spiritual power and it
makes us closer to God. And this is why
this marks a radical turning point in
human history.
Does that make sense, guys? Okay.
Because before you you ask yourself, why
is it there are two billion Christians
in the world? I'm not a Christian by the
way. And why is it that everyone says
that Christianity marks a radical
turning point in human history? And now
Dante provides an answer. Okay? Because
the death of Jesus, the sacrifice of
Jesus is able to rekindle a spark in us
that was once lost. Okay? It's drawing
us closer to God. Before we were on the
wrong path. We were in a desert and we
were lost. And now we see the light and
we're moving towards the light. Okay.
All right. So, do do you guys understand
the logic here?
All right. Any questions about this?
Okay. All right. But you can also see
and this is really important guys.
This beautiful explanation also subverts
Catholic theology.
Okay? Do you you understand? Because
before Catholic theology was based on
vengeance and justice. Now it's based on
love and sacrifice. Does that make sense
guys? Okay.
Before the operating principle was one
of fear of vengeance now it is love
everything happens because
God
loves us and that's why God had to be so
uh careful and deliberate in his
solution to this problem. Okay, got it.
All right, let's let's keep on reading.
Verse 1-7.
And yet these two were things created.
If what has if what has been said above
is true, then these things never should
be subject to corruption.
>> Okay. All right. So um the question is
if it is true that God is perfect,
everything God does is perfect. Why does
imperfection exist in the world? For
example, our bodies, right? Our bodies
are imperfect. We feel pain. We die.
So why is there imp perfection in the
world? Keep on going.
Verse 130. Brother, the angels in the
pure country where you are now, these
may be said to be created as they are in
all their being. Whereas the elements
that you have mentioned, as well as
those things that are made from them,
receive their form from a creative
power. The matter they contain had been
created, just as within the stars that
wheel about them, the power to give form
had been had been created. The rays and
motion of the holy lights draw forth the
soul of every animal and plant from
matter able to take form. But your life
is breathed forth immediately by the
chief good who so enamor it of his own
self that it desires him always.
So reasoning you also can deduce your
resurrection. You need but remember the
way in which your human flesh was
fashioned when both of the first parents
were created.
>> Okay. All right. Okay.
So,
um why is there imperfection in the
world? Why is it that plants wither and
die? Why why is it that we wither and
die? Why?
If God is perfect and everything God
creates is perfect,
then why is there imperfection in the
world? Yes.
>> If everything is perfect, there's no
meaning.
>> Okay. What What does Dante say? I mean,
Dante tells us. Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Because of the original sin.
>> Excuse me.
>> Because of the original sin in the
Garden of Eden when the humans sinned.
But but that doesn't explain the plants
and the animals and decay. Yes.
>> Um so God God is perfect and he make us
imperfect. So therefore we can be uh be
better. Therefore God can be more
perfect.
>> Uh okay. All right. So what what this is
saying, okay, is that
the God's perfection, right? Does God
have the time to create the stone or the
plant?
Does he?
Does God care?
This table, was this created by God?
This table, what what created this
table?
Uh, yes. And h and and how did we create
this table?
From trees. And what created trees?
God created the trees.
>> God created the small trees and become a
big tree, right?
[laughter]
>> So God created seeds.
>> Okay.
Right. So you guys understand God
created the laws of the universe. You
understand the laws of the universe is
is what gives rise to
plants where seeds like become trees
right that's following the law of the
universe but it was God who created
these laws of the universe
and um and then God lets these laws of
universe do what they do. Okay do you
understand? So it's God who created the
law laws of physics who are governed by
the laws of physics. Okay, how are we
different from the other creations in
the world? Okay, all the other creations
in the world are governed by the laws of
physics and biology and chemistry. Okay,
these laws are perfect. These things
that are created are not perfect. We are
different. How are we different?
>> Yes. Um, we have consciousness and we
have free will. So, we can like direct
our own fate and we can like subvert
some laws that like animals are bound to
for example like instincts we can
suppress instincts
>> okay yes but but but like I'm asking you
how this happened right because law god
creates the laws of the universe which
then gives rise to everything including
us we're different but we're different
from everything else right so how was
this possible
yes
>> because we're made in the image of God
but all all the other creatures aren And
so we have his traits I guess or we are
most like him. So we have free will.
>> Yeah. But how did you um how did your
body come into being? Does your body
follow the laws of biology?
Yes, it does. Right.
So what happened? Why are we different
from animals or trees?
>> Oh yeah maybe. Okay. Uh yeah according
to the Bible uh I remember is Genesis it
said that [clears throat] the the God
who just do not allow the the human to
to eat fruits right but the human just
choose to eat the wisdom fruit so so it
means that he betray god right
>> okay guys we are trying to read Dante
okay okay it's like let's let's read
line 139 to the end again okay he tells
you the answer just just read it
carefully
we'll we'll read it we'll read it first
The the rays and motion the rays and
motion of the holy lights draw forth the
soul of every animal and plant from
matter able to take form. But your life
is breathed forth immediately by the
chief good who so enamemers it of his
own self that it desires him always. So
reasoning, you also can deduce your
resurrection. You need but remember the
way in which your human flesh was
fashioned when both of the first parents
were created.
>> Okay. Why are we different from animals
and trees?
Have a soul.
>> You have a soul. How do we know we have
a soul?
>> Yeah. It says here, guys, you have to
read Dante. Okay. Your life is breathed
forth immediately by the chief good.
Okay, do you understand? And how do we
know this? Because it says so in the
Bible, right? How did God create Adam?
You guys know how did God create Adam?
What is Adam crafted by?
>> Dust and soil.
>> Does and then what happens?
breathes into him and brings him to
>> God breathed into him and that's what
gives Adam life. Okay? So in other
words, God put a part of himself in us.
We call this a soul. And because God put
a part of himself in us, what is our
greatest aspiration?
>> To desire him
>> to return to God. You understand? It's
like I give you my finger. Okay? And
like my finger is like I would rather be
part of a hole. Okay? So your finger is
always desiring to return to him. Do you
understand? Okay. So that's what this is
saying. This is saying that God breathed
himself into us. There's an aspect of
God in us and this aspect is always
looking to return to God. At the same
time, God is always calling for us to
return to him. Okay? And this is a
fundamental logic of the universe.
Everything we do is because we want to
return to God.
Okay? It doesn't mean we know how to do
so, but we want to do so, right?
Does that make sense?
>> Then then why do we need to live in the
first place? Like why do why do we need
to
live?
>> Why did God create Adam?
What what does the Bible say?
Why did God create Adam?
>> God wanted relationship.
>> He was lonely, man.
>> Yeah.
>> He wanted to know himself. He was
lonely,
right? Yes.
>> So I have a question. So according to
this theoretical framework like you have
humans and you have other life as in
planted animals. So technically planted
animals are closer to God than we are
because they live in perfect almost
blind obedience to God's natural laws.
That is the laws of physics and the laws
of biology while we humans con
consistently defy these these laws.
>> No, that's the complete opposite of what
what I what I just said. Yes.
>> None of them have souls.
>> Okay. So God creates a universe. The
universe is governed by these laws that
he creates. Okay. Okay, the laws of
physics. This gives rise to everything
including evolution which creates us,
right? What makes what makes us unique
is God touched us. God put a part of
himself into us. And this part of our
ourselves that we don't really know the
soul. What it what it always desires is
return to the whole. We're a part we
want to return to the whole. Okay.
Everything we do is because we desire to
return to the whole.
Okay.
Does that make sense? That's our
greatest desire to return to the whole.
We may not know it. We may be we may be
ignorant of it, but that's what we what
we truly truly aspire to.
Okay. All right.
Um, so reasoning you can deduce your own
resurrection.
You need remember the way in which your
human flesh was fashioned when both of
the first parents were created. What
does this mean?
What's the message here?
>> Yes.
>> Go ahead.
>> So basically he was saying that um both
of the first parents refer to Adam and
Eve obviously and basically he is
restating that thing in Christianity
where the soul is immortal. So if you
can remember a time before your corrupt
flesh, then you're immoral now.
>> Yes. Exactly. Okay. Uh sorry. Did do you
want to say something? Okay. So what
this is saying is like remember that you
think you're a body. You think you're a
human. But what you are really is an
aspect of God. That's what your soul is,
an aspect of God. And that makes you
eternal. Okay? So in other words, you
can't possibly die. You can only be
reborn
and re be reborn. Okay. So if this is
the case,
what's the purpose of life?
Right? Because today you're taught that
the purpose purpose of life is to seek
immortality, to live forever, to be
wealthy,
right? Don't die.
But this is telling us, well, you
weren't going to die anyway. Who cares?
Then what's the purpose of life then?
>> Yes.
>> Somehow I believe life is just about
being happy, making yourself as happy as
possible without harming other people.
But I'm pretty sure that this is the
perspective that Dante explicitly
disagrees with.
>> What would Dante say?
>> Um, well, he rejects the materialism of
the Catholic Church, obviously. And
basically he's the pilgrim Dante is
alive here. He is uh flesh and blood
here and yet he isoop he is climbing up
to heaven. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. He's b
up into heaven. So basically what what
he's trying to say what I think he's
trying to say is that uh we have to
pursue not material pleasures but a
spiritual good.
>> Okay. So um anyone else? What what's the
point of our existence? Oh yeah, maybe
because the god just try to come back.
So he just hope that people can bring
him back because we're the part of them.
We're just like maybe a single or what?
He just wait us to to bring him back
just like we make machine man, right? Or
Robert Robert will sometime bring us.
>> So So you see like God wants to come
here.
>> Yeah, he will come back because he leave
away, right? He will come back. So just
like he said, I will come back if you
trust me and I will come back. I I don't
understand why God wants to come here.
>> Okay. Anyone else?
>> Yeah.
>> I think in the last few lines he kind of
says that we want to desire him. So to
know him and become like him, I guess.
And just like even in paradise, you want
to get closer to him even in paradise.
>> Yeah. But I'm saying how do you do that
then?
I guess to know him and be more like him
or desire.
>> I I I know but I'm saying how
right
>> I think I think Dante would Dante would
say um the point of life is to to love
and to imagine use imagination.
>> Okay. So these things are the same
thing. The the the goal is to love.
Okay.
Why would that
be the most important
thing you can do in life?
Yeah, because God is love. I understand
that God is love.
Um,
but what's different?
But what's different between our world
and his world? Why are we here?
Yes. Um because we I mean according to
Dante like we're fragments of this love,
right? If God is love, we are fragments
of this love and we our journey for each
and every one of us is to return to the
source. So
I just
>> Okay, but then like why don't you kill
yourself like right now?
>> No, you wouldn't you wouldn't be able to
return to the source if you kill
yourself. That's not that's that will
lead you. Then then how do we return to
the source?
>> To love to amplify whatever that is
within us which was breathed into us in
order to to to get closer to the source.
>> Okay.
Anyone else?
We should act in accordance with natural
law.
>> What is natural law?
>> The morality that's set up by God.
>> Okay. Right. Okay. Try to be specific.
Okay. Yes. Did did you have a Okay. All
right.
Anyone else? Yes.
>> Maybe we should try to exper experience
more.
>> We we should experience more
>> because God can can't experience as a
human.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. Okay. So, let's
do a film about this. Okay. Everything
God does is perfect. Everything God does
is for a perfect reason.
He created this world which is governed
by perfect laws but it's imperfect in
that well uh there's evil, there's pain,
there's hunger, there's agony, there's
suffering.
What's the point of all this?
Why would he create a world like this?
Yes. Well, if I didn't know about whole
baptism thing, I would say that we are
here and we have to live a full life and
we have to live a good life because we
have original sin and we have to redeem
our souls which are after all afflicted
with original sin from the Adam and Eve
business from original sin. But there's
this whole baptism thing and therefore
my explanation is null and void.
>> Okay. All right. So an idea that you
guys need to remember is like we don't
have to redeem ourselves because Jesus
already did it for us. Do you
understand? Okay.
This is a major assumption of divine
comedy. So now the question then is if
we're redeemed, everything that we
everything that um is done is for a
purpose. Everything is in the in the
mind of God. Everything he does is for a
perfect reason.
What is the purpose of this world that
we live in?
Uh [clears throat] maybe there's uh you
know just like experiment how about
we're living uh in the two world the one
world is perfect world just what god
created there's no misery no no saying
everything is perfect but the other
world is like us where maybe just like
hell you know we're in agony and we are
in despair so maybe God try to test or
try to make experiment just like we we
put the rats into two maze right and try
to find out uh if just give them the
right the food and and I like to to to
circle around a maze so the the right
will try to knock down the door and try
to find the food. So maybe Yeah.
>> Yes. Yes. Go ahead.
>> Maybe because love is made perfect in
pain and agony maybe like that way. So
it's
>> can can you explain
>> like you cannot show or exercise or
prove love without paying a price for
it. So then the other side of the coin
is that you have to pay a price or you
have to deal with some sort of ugly evil
things to see what's beautiful maybe to
>> Yeah. But I mean like why would God do
this? What's the point of this?
Okay. All right. Let me ask you this
question.
What is it that we have
that
God doesn't have?
flesh. Human body.
>> Okay. Is that impressive?
>> Mortality.
>> Mortality. Death. Yes.
>> Imperfection.
>> Imperfection. Yes.
>> Evilness.
>> We can be evil. Yes. Okay. Um. Okay.
Let's let's now step back and think
about what's happening. Okay. Beatrice
and Dante are together, right?
What is the relationship?
>> Teacher, student.
>> Exactly. It's teacher student, right?
Because D is asking questions and
Beatric is providing answers. Are Beat's
answers perfect?
Are they perfect?
Are they the absolute truth? Yes, they
are.
Yeah, I understand. You can argue with
her, but I'm saying like in
>> I'm saying that in the in par in
paradiso itself like Beatatrice admitted
that her her words are but an imperfect
reflection of the truth like she is
trying to communicate the truth but she
is doing it to Dante and Dante is not
able to take the truth in his present
form.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. Let's Okay. Let's
take it step by step. Okay. First, we've
established that the relationship
between Beatatrice and Dante is teacher
student. Okay, that's point one. Point
two is even though you could be right
and like what Beatric, how Beatric
expresses herself where Dante is
imperfect, her understanding of the
universe is perfect. Correct. Yes.
Because she represents God. Everything
she says is perfect. We may not
understand what she says. Donna may
misinterpret what she says, but
everything she says is perfect. Okay,
that's number two.
Number three then is
what then is the point of teaching Dante
>> so that he can be the mouthpiece and
tell people
>> okay
>> like a prophet
>> so so historically
>> I can I answer
>> well Dante the divine comedy is you go
through hell first to get to heaven so
earth is hell and you can learn in from
all the materialistic things you can
learn if they're good or not and then
return to God yourself. But you have to
go through inferno first.
>> Okay. All right. So in the Bible there
is a book called Ezekiel. Okay. Ezekiel
actually draw it up. Okay. Okay.
Right. So we're ask Google. Okay. How
does Ezekiel receive the word of God?
All right. So Ezekiel, it's a book of
the Bible and he he goes up to heaven
and he goes up to heaven to receive the
word of God just like Dante is receiving
the word of God. How does Ezekiel
receive the word of God? Do you think
Okay. So a is stupid. Okay. No, no, no.
If you read the Bible, okay, how does
Ezekiel literally receive the word of
God
to me?
>> Could speak to God. He had a
relationship with God.
>> No, no, no.
What God did was take the scrolls,
right? The scrolls carry his message and
then and then what what what did God do?
He stuffed it
into the mouth of Ezekiel and Ezekiel
literally ate it. Do you understand? If
you want to make sure the prophet
delivers the right message, you stuff it
down his throat. Do you understand?
So why is Peter wasting all this time
dealing with Dante?
Yes. Did Ezekiel agree to have this
stuff down his throat?
>> Um, so like Dante is going through this
experience uh and not just have all of
the information stuffed down his throat
because the journey is what matters more
than the information.
>> Don't you think accuracy matters more?
Like if God wants to deliver message to
his people, don't you think like
accuracy matters?
>> Right? I think it's not about like is it
maybe it's the idea that it's not
the end result or the accuracy. There's
not a right answer, but it's the
individual transformation and the
individual journey that matters more.
>> Why though? I'm trying to figure this
out. Okay, I'm trying to figure out
Okay, like in Ezekiel, you can just
stuff the message down a person's throat
so that so that he never forgets it.
Okay, and all and he must quote it word
for word.
Right.
But not only does
Dante But not only does Beatus not stuff
anything down her throat, but what
happens after Dante goes home? Do Do you
guys remember what happens a after he
goes home?
>> He forgets a bunch of things.
>> He forgets everything.
>> Not everything.
>> Basically everything. Okay.
This is like really weird to like forgot
to deliver a message to people. Like,
let's pick a guy who I have to teach and
then he'll probably forget most of most
everything I teach and he's going to go
back and he's going to have to remember
everything. Okay,
this is a really silly way of doing
things, but God is perfect. Everything
God does is is for a reason. So, what's
the reason? So, can it can it be that
God wants us to utilize our one gift
that he's given us, free will, to freely
choose to be nearer to him, and we each
have to take that trip or that process
individually? Dante can't take that trip
for us.
>> Yeah, that that is correct. Okay. So,
how can Dante
deliver this message or how can Dante
help us go on this journey ourselves?
by by writing this book.
>> Exactly. There you go. That this is why
this had to happen. Okay.
What is it that we have that God doesn't
have? How is Donnie able to write this?
>> We have a concept of space and time.
>> So like
>> how how did Donnie write this?
>> Yes.
Oh. Oh, I know. Um, we h we don't know
things. God is all knowing. God knows
everything. So, we can
>> How did write the divine harmony?
>> He's channeling God.
>> He channel God, but it was through him,
right? So, what did he do?
>> Think that he utilized uh the things
that he was trying to preach against as
in logic and rationalism. What did he
use to create this thing?
>> Pencil and paper.
>> Do you guys not have it?
>> Imagination.
>> The imagination. Do you understand?
What's it that we have that God cannot
have? The imagination. Why can I God
have imagination?
He's perfect. You understand?
If you're perfect, you know everything.
You cannot fail. Therefore, you cannot
have an imagination.
Okay?
That's why Beatrice cannot come to our
world and communicate with us directly
because she lacks the imagination to do
so.
Right? That's the entire point of this
journey. Dante must go through this
journey himself in order to experience
the truth of God. But then he must use
his imagination in order to help us go
on our own journey. And that is by
writing divine comedy. The entire
purpose of his visit to heaven was so
that he could write the divine comedy.
Okay. Basically, he's a journalist and
he's been invited to heaven to do some
reporting and come back and then write
in a very nice way so that we can all go
on this journey our ourselves. Okay.
That's why Dante had to go to heaven.
That's why he had to write Divine
Comedy. Okay? So that we can by
ourselves go on this journey to heaven
and discover what God truly is. Does
that make sense, guys?
Again, everything God does is for a
perfect reason. If you don't know it,
it's because you're not thinking hard
enough.
Okay. Yes. Okay, this might be pushing
the point here, but if God is perfect
and there's nothing that we have that he
doesn't have, then how does we have
imagination and he doesn't?
>> Yeah, that's a good question. Why?
What is that we have that God doesn't
have?
>> Oh, yeah. Maybe maybe because God is
invincible because God can live forever.
But but life is limited. So people have
imagination because if you're limited,
so you just always want to know more
about
>> Yeah. Exactly. Yes. Go on. Imagination
isn't a skill that something you have.
It's something that you lack. So if you
already know everything, there's nothing
to imagine. But we can imagine because
we have gaps in our thinking.
>> So
>> yeah, because our lives are limited. We
want to transcend to um higher realms or
higher consciousness. We that's why we
imagine.
>> Okay. Yeah. But the major point is that
[clears throat] what D is saying is that
we humans are not um lesser beings. We
are co-equal with God because even even
though God has perfection, we have
imagination.
And so if you're God and you're trying
to extend the boundaries of the
universe, right? You're trying to create
more things in the universe, you can't
do do so yourself because you're
perfection. Okay? So you must use
humanity.
So everything that happens
is for a divine purpose.
You understand? And as you say, the
reason why we have we have the
imagination is because we have bodies
and our bodies can suffer, bodies can
feel pain, bodies can die.
And what excites the imagination is the
fact that we can ask questions. We can
make mistakes.
We can not know. Okay.
Does that make sense?
Yes.
>> So, we're going quantity over quality
here, right? Because God could create
anything he wants, but he is absolutely
perfect. So, he is tired of having to
create everything. And so, he wants
people to create more things that he
couldn't think of. But these things are
going to be imperfect because these
people who create are going to be
imperfect too. Is that right?
>> Um
okay.
So let's just say you're God. Okay. And
you want you want to create a perfect
world and you do create a perfect world.
What's the problem with that?
It becomes eternal, right? What what is
eternity?
Nothing ever changes.
>> Eternity is death. You understand that?
Eternity is death.
So your only solution to life is
infinity.
Does that make sense? God is eternal. We
are infinite.
Love is eternal. The imagination is
infinite.
Okay? God is not capable of the
imagination.
Therefore, God had to create us.
Okay?
Does it make sense to you guys?
>> Yeah. Um well actually I think God maybe
just want to us forever because in the
in the Bible is that the people they
they don't need to wear clothes they're
naked and they got surrounded by the
light. They're in the light ball. So it
mean they will live forever. But just
because the people who just you know try
maybe out of curiosity so is been rural
by the snake. So it's just sitting
right. So just eat a fruit and there's
another tray
instead of the the tree with the fruit
uh with the wisdom there's another trade
that is the longevity but the people
just choose to to pick the fruit from
the wisdom.
>> Okay. Okay. All right.
>> Yeah. Okay. Yes. [clears throat]
>> Well, I have a unrelated question. So um
why haven't anybody else traveled to
paradise and write a uh book just like
Dante?
Why there's a billions of people that
only Dante have went to paradise
and wrote a book?
>> What's the answer?
Uh uh well I I don't know if I can
answer a question but I do uh you know
just like I maybe I was in my dream that
I I can see something in my dream that I
was in hell and in hell uh people just
feel suffer but there's another place
that I also can saw in my dream is that
people think everything is for free
everything is for free so that's really
chaotic yeah maybe maybe there's so many
universe some of the universe Because
you know people just like beast some of
the universe.
>> Why was there a Jesus?
>> Why couldn't Why couldn't there be a
second Jesus? There was only one Jesus.
Why was there just one Jesus? Someone
else can't come and be another Jesus.
Why not?
>> Because Jesus is uh a facet of God. And
if we if another Jesus comes in and also
says, "Oh, we're going to redeem you of
all your sins." Then that's basically
saying the first Jesus didn't do his
job. So the first Jesus will be
imperfect. And that wouldn't be very
nice, that would it? Okay. Okay. So, I
think Dante was a messenger from God.
Okay. So, you asked a question earlier
today. How did Dante How was Dante able
to do what he did? Okay. So, here's some
facts about Dante.
The man died without a country. He was
in exile.
He was living off the generosity of his
patrons. And after he finished Divine
Comedy in 1321, he died a few months
later. Okay? He didn't experience any
fame, he was never paid for the divine
comedy. And as you can see, it is really
hard. Okay, it's hard for us to read it,
but imagine how hard it is to write it.
But he was doing it without a particular
reward. What was his reward for doing
this?
He was not famous in his time. He he
became famous later. In fact, while he
was alive, he was despised by his own
people, the Florentines.
In fact, um the Catholic Church was so
angry at him, they were they actually
wanted like to dig up his body and burn
him at the stake.
Okay. So,
what motivated the man? how he's able to
focus 20 years of his life on running
something that may or may not have been
burned by the Catholic Church, that may
or may not be read by people. Okay?
And the only answer that I think makes
sense is
the moment he was born,
he knew what his mission was.
And throughout his entire life,
the divine comedy in his complete form
appeared to him in certain fragments.
And in his head, he kept on
um imagining these different parts. And
then when he finally conceptualized the
entirety of Divine Comedy, he then wrote
it down. Okay?
And why I say this is
okay I have problems understanding
what motivated man for 20 years to write
the divine comedy but also like think
about the impact of the divine comedy in
our world. Not only is divine comedy the
source for the renaissance, it's also
the source for the Protestant
Reformation, Sic Revolution, the
Enlightenment, modernity itself. It
changed the entire world by itself.
And you're telling me this is all an
accident. And you're telling me, oh
well, you know, he's he's just got
lucky. 20 years
every day working his ass off to put
this together. not knowing if it'll be
read one day
and
100 year 100 years after it is published
it forever changed to the world. It is
recognized today as the most important
literary achievement in human history.
Today we read it and we can see its
power even though we are no longer part
of his world. Right? Even if you don't
know any history,
you can still read the Divine Comedy and
feel its beauty, feel its power. How is
this possible? Unless this is all
designed by God. Unless Dante was a
messenger of God himself and he knew
from an early age this is his mission
and he structured his entire life for
this mission.
I don't know. Yes. Um again I think
that's a very absolute perspective and
it I think it actually diminishes the
value of Dante and of the divine comedy
as a humanist. So uh the Renaissance is
characterized by his humanism while it
is not separate from in the Catholic
church while it's still heavily
influenced by religion. I think it's
important to know that Dante was a great
person and that he did not need a god to
make his writing even greater.
Similarly, we do not need a god to
understand to understand what Dante
Dante wrote to appreciate it for its
greatness. I think as humans, our value
is enough.
>> Okay. Um I don't disagree with what you
say. Okay. But like like I want to
emphasize certain points about this
class. Okay. First of all, this is not
an academic seminar.
This is about
intellectual speculation. It's about
going on a journey like Dante went on
his journey to figure out the structure,
the secrets of the universe itself.
That's point one. Point two is on this
journey it has to be leap of faith.
Okay? You have to believe that this is
divine. You have to believe this is
perfection. You have to believe that
when you enter the divine comedy, you
are entering into the soul of the
universe itself. And my argument to you
is that if you take this leap of faith,
if you open your heart, if you open your
mind and you fully embrace divine
comedy, you'll be transformed by it.
Okay? And you know what? If it is not
true, there's actually no harm to you.
Okay? But if I'm correct, this could be
the most life transforming experience in
your life. So why not just take the
risk? put away
your delusions or your beliefs about our
world and fully embrace divinity.
Okay? And I'm saying only by doing that
can you truly appreciate the divine
comedy. Is that clear to you guys?
>> Okay. Okay. That's it for today. We'll
continue tomorrow. Okay.